<sec_map><section><chunk>Free-text Answers Underpinned by the Combination of a BLEU -inspired Algorithm and Latent Semantic Analysis Diana P erez 1 , Allo Gliozzo 2 , Carlo Strapparava 2 , Enrique Alfonseca 1 ,Pilar Rodr guez 1 and Bernardo Magnini 2 </chunk></section><section /><section><chunk>2 Istituto per la Ricerca Scientiica e Tecnologica (IRST), 38050 Trento, Italy fgliozzo,strappa,magnini g@itc.it Abstract  In previous work we have proved that the B LEU algo- rithm (Papineni et al. 2001), originally devised for eval- uating Machine Translation systems, can be applied to assessing short essays written by students. In this pa- per we present a comparative evaluation between this BLEU -inspired algorithm and a system based on Latent Semantic Analysis. In addition we propose an effective combination schema for them. Despite the simplicity of these shallow NLP methods, they achieve state-of-the- art correlations to the teachers scores while keeping the language-independence and without requiring any do- main speciic knowledge. </chunk></section><section><heading>Introduction </heading><chunk>Assessing students answers is a very time-consuming ac- tivity that makes teachers cut down the time they can devote to other duties. In some cases, they may even have to re- duce the number of assignments given to their students due to lack of time. Many researchers believe that computers can be used to help the teachers in their assessment task. This is the basis of the eld known as Computer-Assisted Assess- ment (CAA) of free-text answers. CAA of free-text answers is a long-standing problem that has attracted interest from the research community since the sixties (Page 1966) and has not been fully solved yet. On the other hand, the success of e-learning and the advances in other areas such as Information Extraction (IE) and Natu- ral Language Processing (NLP) have made CAA of free-text answers a ourishing research line in the last few years. A computer can examine and analyze essays in much more de- tail than a human teacher, as is totally free of any kind of judgements, myths, false beliefs and value biases (Streeter et al. 2003). In the literature, several techniques have been used to tackle this problem with increasingly better results. They can be grouped into ve main categories: statisti- cal, NLP, IE, clustering, and integrated-approaches (Valenti, Neri, &amp; Cucchiarelli 2003). In previous work we presented Atenea (Alfonseca &amp; P erez 2004), a system for scoring automatically open ended Copyright c 2005, American Association for Artiicial Intelli- gence (www.aaai.org). All rights reserved. questions. According to the already introduced tion, it is an integrated approach, since it relies on nation of a B LEU (Papineni et al. 2001) inspired algorithm, called Evaluating Responses with B LEU (ERB) (P erez, Al- fonseca, &amp; Rodr guez 2004a), with a set of NLP techn such as stemming, closed-class word removal, W Disambiguation and synonyms treatment proc particular, the ERB algorithm performs a synta of the students answers. However, we believe that, in order to fully answers, both a syntactic and a semantic ana quired. Thus we decided to include a semantic Atenea, based on Latent Semantic Analysis (L has been successfully applied to evaluating fr swers, as reported in (Foltz, Laham, &amp; Land Dessus, Lemaire, &amp; Vernier 2000). Then we exp neas infrastructure to combine ERB with LSA, tutes the original contribution of this paper. E results connrm the hypothesis of the natural com ity of syntax and semantics, by reporting a sign provement in the accuracy of the combined syste It is usually very difcult to perform a comparis text CAA systems due to the lack of common c standard metrics. Nevertheless, because in our c apply the same experimental settings for the L ERB techniques, we have the possibility of doi rst time a comparative analysis of both ERB an common set of students and teachers answers. to perform this comparison in order to study h statistical approaches can fullll the same goal. ation purposes, the Pearson correlation coefcie the humans scores and the systems scores is cal It is also interesting to study how far we can go of assessing students answers by only exploiting NLP techniques, such as ERB and LSA. Shallow niques can be easily implemented for any langu ically, they do not require ad-hocc lexical reso domain speciic knowledge. The only resource re both ERB and LSA is a corpus of students ans also exploits a large collection of domain specii induce lexical knowledge in a totally unsupervis the Web era, collections of non-annotated texts available. The paper is organized as follows: in Section Atenea we n raa rrenn e rr nn aa a a r aa a ee B LE Paa a nenn ee aa a e re ea ee e aa a a rr r r r r aa e re ar a enn n ann n er e ann n n aa e e e eaa a a err r ann n err e ree erenn ee e ee e er ann n nn ee enn n n a e a er ree BLE ee a MM M M M ee nn n ee Pree e e e e n MM PP ee rr r aa e ree e enn e nn n raa aa a a rr r nn e nn n n er ee aa a earr n e ann n n aa e ann n e ree erenn ee e MM P e aa a a a aa ee r eaa aa a e n aa a a rann ee rr r r nn er n raa a rr r e ann n n aa e e e nn n n ee e nn ee n e ree erenn ee e Ne a ee e e e ee e arr r r r r M PP err r rr ee e n e aa a ee e a enaa a a aa a a n aa a a a ee err rr ann err r e nn n n n n ee ee nn e ree aa a e a Bre Pena BPP aa a a r e a e ee e rr r r naa aa a a rr r r r aa aa ee nn n aa a a a nn nn n nn n e ree e e e e n e rr r r naa B LE ree aa a a e ree aa a aa aa a a a aa ee nn e err enn n aa e e ree erenn ee aa eree e enn n ann n er P eree e AA A A nn ee aa RR R r ee nn a M ee Bre Penaa a a MBPP aa a a r e a e aa a ee B LE nn n n ree aa a a rr r r r EE aa a aa a nn Ree e e nn ee BLE ERBB B EE E aa a a n e naa rr r r a r a aa a nn e re an ann n er a n ree ree enn n e enn n n e n raa a a ann n N e ee e aa a e an n an aa ee ERB score (a) = M BP (a) e N n=0 log(M U P (n)) N ll oll l l inn n n n n nn ii n nn ii i i nii i i o ii i i i nn oo o o o nn i ill l ii i in ognii i nn nn ii ii oo o o inn n oo o ing ingg ll l ll l oo o oo ii ion oo oo o o o nn n ii D e raa a ee rr r a ar e aa e rr r r r n er rr r r err rrenn ee n e rr r are aa a a ree eann a enn naa a a a ree e e e e n eraa ee n e aa rr r D e ee e e rr n e rr r r naa aa e are aa a ee n a er enn n n naa aa ee n e arr enee e rr r r ee aa a earr r ann arr r r ee e e e aa a a n re aa a a raa ee e ree e e e e nn LSA ee e rr an e e ee ee e e e aa e err ann enn arr r r Re arr r nn enn arr r r e ee a arr aa a a n e ee e e e e e e e e enn ee e e e e e e e e ee e rr r ee n Berrr n eaa a enn ree ree enn ee e e nn rr aa a a ee LSA ee e e rr r aa a e err r nn aa nee n aa a a rr r nn e ee e e e e nn ee a nn n ee n nn n rr aa a a n Ree rr e aa ann e Caa e rr r aa a a n See aa a a ann aa een aa a ee Deerr ee e er ee aa a aa a n e LSA aa ee ee e ee e aa a a a a a a a a err aa an ree er erenn nn ee e e e ann nn nn n n ee e aa a aa e aa e nn ee e e n a nn e an e ree erree erenn err r are ree ree enn ee e err rr ann nn n n er e aa a ee e e en e aa a aa a nn enn n n ann n err r r e aa a a e ann aa a a a an e ee ee nn n e a er, ar ee e e re aa a enn e n e ee e C OM P ER SC ENCE ann a erenn ne n e ee e B LD N ND S R PP P P P ee e ann nn n are ee ee e nn e nn n rr aa a a n rr r an e ernaa rr r r r rr nn e ee an aa a rr r rr r ee ann n n nn ee e e aa a a a e ann n aa ee ree ree enn ee a rr r r r re ee ann n n aa a a re aa ee err r r SS S S rr r r r re aa a a e ee eee re an e nn enn aa a a aa a a e ree e ee e rr r ee e ee e ee e rr nn e err r r aa e ree enn n n n aa nee a er rr nn aa a a a nn n e LSA aa a a rr r r r e a e ee e aa a aa e e enn n n ann n err ee nee aa . ee a e e ee e e e e e e e e enn ee e e r aa nee rr r e enn n ann n er a ann ee R = r , r , . . . , r n e e see oo e see e o occ c enn ecc ors corress onn inn o e ree erencess e score is ee nee e ee n oo e see e oo o occ c enn sii ii i rii ies ee e een a ann r i R re en nn rr aa a a ee n rr er ree e rn a aa a e n e rann e aa ee nee ee e aa a a n LSA score (a) = riR cos( a, r i ) 2 R + 0.5 (2) coo o o o o o o oo oo oo o o o o s ss s ss s s s s s s s s ss s cc o oo ss s c ss s oo o o o o oo o ccc sss s o soo o cc c cc c sss sss s s s s oo cc c coo ss s s s s s cc oo ss ss s s s oo o o o o s s ss s s o coo o o o o so cc c cc oo o s ss s s ss s s s s cc c c oo o o o cc s oo cc c sss s s s cc c c ss s oo o o o o ss ss s s coo oo scc c c c (( ( oo o o o 2002)) coo o o o o o o oo scc c c c oo o o o o oo o s s ss s s s s ss s oo oo o o o o ss scc c c c c COM B score (a) = ERB score (a) + (1 )LSA score (a) (( ) a araa ee er aa aa a a aa a a a n n aa a ann e a ee e e e ERB r LSAA n e naa a a n ee a ee ee e e e ann err eneraa a en e ee e aa ee e e e e are aa a a a nee ee e e n r e err r enn n e a e aa a a rr ee e n e ee e ee e aa eaa a re e er nn r naa a a n ee e e e e EE E err r enn aa ee e e nn n e aa a aa e r ee e e e nn ne erenn enn n n arr aa a ee e rr r reaa e a n SS ann n n n ann an aa a a a a a naa ne ee nn n n nn aa nee rr r e arr P eree e AA A nn ee aa RR R r ee aa a e en ee e are ee e rr r ee n aa a e r eaa a ee e e e nn e ee e ee a ee enn n n ann n err ann e aa a ee erenn an ee aa a a a n SEE BLEE ERB SAA LSA CS LSA Mean aa a e . EE aa a aa a a n BLL EE ERBB SAA LSA ann CSS LSAA e rr r n nn n n aa ee e ee e e e n nn n n er e nn nee ree e rr e rree aa a a n ann n ree aa a a e ee B LE ERBB SAA LSA ann CSS LSAA e aa a rr ree e rr r e ean rree aa a a nn n a re eaa a ee e e aa a a rr r e e ree erenn e ann err r eaa a ee e e e nn e ee ree erenn e ann n err e nn n nn ee e e rr e ree e e ree ERBB e LSA neee e an aa a a a a a naa aa n ee e e rr r r e raa nee e e n ee e ee enn n n ann n err aa a a err r rr a araa a e anaa a a a a ERBB LSA ann ee r naa a a nn r e aa a aa a a n rr r r ee e e Pearr r nn rree aa n ee enn ee e een e ann n ree ann e ee e ree aa a a a aa ee e raa n e LSA ee e ee e nn r ra. SA. a aa a rr r r ee SS S S enn Ann er ee e ee n an OO eraa a nn SS S S ee e rr ee e a e een aa a a a aa a a a rann n aa ee rr r SS ann n n Enn nn AA A a a Baa ee e e e ree err e a r ree e e aa a aa a a n ee e e e e e e e e nn ne e enn n n ann err nn aa nee n rr r r nn n n n ee n e e aa a a aa a a n aa aa ee e e CS. a ar e ee e e e n e rr r e Da arr e NN rr r AA err r a CC C C ee e e e n rr r r r nn n n n n Enn n n n n e raa a a ann arr r ee rr r CC C C er SS S enn e aa aa a nee aa PC eee PC er r PC Ma aa a ne ann arr r r r ee ree aa ee CC C C C C er SS S enn e n re enerr r rnaa a a aa e Ne rr ee r BB B B nee e eee EE aa a aa a a n n ee e e e n e e aa a aa e nn ee enn enn n n e ERB ann e LSA ee e n a n ee e ee e ee e rr r e n e ree n a re rr AA A A nn ee a P eree e a e err ee aa ree e e e e aa nee ERB nn n ee reaa e en nn an aa a a a aa a a rann n aa a a n ee rr e enn n n ann n er ann er ann n aa ee Bee aa a e e rr r r ee r raa nn nn LSA n Enn n n n n n AA A a a Baa ee e e e .. . . . rr r r aa a aa a a a aa a a a a aa een ee rann n aa e e S ann n n raa nn nn ann e aa a aa a a n ee Enn n n n n n rr er aa e a arr r r n e Enn n n n n Da CC rr r r aa ee n e er e err r enn n n = 0.5 s oo o s coo o o o o o o o ss oo s ss cc c oo o ss o s oo coo o o o o o oo o ss s s s oo s ss oo s ss o 22 s oo oo o coo o oo o scc c c oo s ss cc c oo o s ss s cc c o oo o ss s s s s s ss s cc c c c c c ss ss cc ss ss s s s oo o o o oo o s oo o o o o o o oo o o o o s oo o ccc c c c c s ss s s s so ss o ccc c c c oo o s coo o o s s ss s oo ss s s s s s ss s oo o o coo o o s scc c c c s ss s oo s oo cc oo o s so coo o o o o o o o o o o o oo oss oo s oo ss cc c c ss ss s s s ss oo ss s oo s oo ss ss s coo o o o o o coo o coo o o o o o o o o o o o o oo o s s o coo o oo o o o o ss ss s s coo o o o o o o oo scc c c c scc c c c c oo ss s oo o o osss s s s s s s s s cc coo o o o o o oo o ss s s s cc c c oo cc (( ( ( ( oo ) oo o ss s s s s s c oo cc (( ( ( ( ( ( )) ss cc c c c c c oo o o o osss s s s s s s s ss ss s s s oo o o o s ss o s oo o o o cc s oo ss ss s s s oo o o o o o o coo o o o o o o oo coo o o o o o ss ss s s s aa a a a n e a eraa e re e a ee aa a naa e rree aa a a nn aa a a e ee earr r aa e naa a a n ee a ee ee e e e. e ee e r e naa a a n BLEE ann CSS LSAA n aa a aa ee e ree e e e e nee ee ee e er an e ree e e e e aa ann n aa a ne aa a aa a a nn n nn eree e e nn n n en nee ERBB SAA LSA ann CSS LSA rr e e aa e enee e e e e en CSS LSA aa a ne re a raa e an SAA LSAA ee e ar e an r naa a a n ee e e e e e aa a a ee e e e aa ee e ee e araa ee er ee e e nn n n nn e araa ee er n e ee e ee e e ean rree aa a a nn e nee ee e are ree e rr ee n aa a e n e aa e aa a e e aa a a ree e rr e aa a e e araa ee er e ee a e e e ee e ree e e e e e aa n ee e nn n n ee e ee e naa a a n ERB ann CSS LSAA BLEE ERB SEE SAA LSA CSS LSA SAA LSA CSS LSA Mean AA A A a aa a e . EE aa a aa a a n e nee ee e nn e araa ee er Cee e e ree e rr r e ean rree aa a a nn ann e aa a ee aa e aa a a e ee a rree aa a a n aa nn n n n n n ee e e ree e e e eaa a ree n r e err r enn n EE en e erenn e nn n err nn n n ann n e e er naa ar e rr r r ee raa n e CSS LSA a een rr ee ee e e e e aa a a n naa a a n ERBB e ee e aa a a raa aa een aa nee nn nn ERB ann CSS LSA ann ee e nn eann aa a er ee e e e aa een aa a a a nee ERBB n eneraa a nn ere nn aa en nn nn ERBB ree ann LSA ree nn e erenn ee e e e e e aa nee ee e ree ere e ee e rr ee enn n e rree aa a a n e ann n ree e AA e ee e e LSA aa a a raa rr ee en a rr r r rr ee r raa nn nn n e en e SA rr r r ee e rr r ee e ee e e e nn aa n n re ee aa a a On e er ann n e enee e e e er rr r r are enn n n n n ree e e ee en LSA nee ERBB e a ree e ann nn n nn e eann aa a n r aa ee e en nn a enerr r rr r r ee a rr r r aa ee nn n nn n e arr r r r r ar ree erenn ee e ee e e e nn aa e a e e aa a aa ee e raa n e LSA ee e aa a a raa n e aa a a a aa a a rr nn rr r ee e an e rr ee e CC nn n n n n n nn ann re rr n aa er e a e ee e ee e ee e e aa nn nn erenn nn ee e e rr ee ann aa a a rr r r r r a aa a e raa e r an aa a a a aa a a aa a ee e e enn enn n n reee e e ann n err r n arr r r r r ar e a e ree enn ee a naa a a n ee a r erenn ee e nn n n ee . ERB ann LSAA ee e nn n raa e r aa a e a e are e err r rr ann ee eaa a ee e nn n n e n e n e err r enn aa raa e rr rr ee AA eneaa en e a e e aa a aa ee ee r naa nn e ree e e e e aa a ee e ee aa ann n aa a ne ee e ERB err r rr r e err r CC nn ernn nn LSAA nn a rr r r rr ee aa a a raa aa a a aa a e ee erenn aa nn n ee e e nn aa n ee e e e enn n raa n e LSA ee e naa a a n ee a r ERB ann LSA aa aa a a een </chunk></section></sec_map>