<sec_map><section><chunk>www.eamt2015.org MAY 11-13, 2015 WOW TOPK API PALACE ANTALYA / TURKEY THE 18 th ANNUAL CONFERENCE OF THE EUROPEAN ASSOCIATION FOR MACHINE TRANSLATION (EAMT 2015) Organized by Edited by IIknur Durgar El-Kahlout Mehmed Ozkan Felipe Sanchez-Martinez Gema Ramirez-Sanchez Fred Hollowood Andy Way i  EAMT 2015  Proceedings of the 18 th  Annual Conference of the   European Association for Machine Translation  Antalya, Turkey   May 11  13, 2015 at the WOW Topkap Palace  Edited by  IIknur Durgar ElKahlout  Mehmed Ozkan   Felipe SanchezMartinez   Gema RamirezSanchez   Fred Hollowood  Andy Way  ii  Contents  Foreword   iii  Preface by the Programme Chairs   v  Message from the Conference Chair  vi  EAMT 2015 Committees   vii  Sponsors   x  List of papers    xi  Invited talk by Olga Beregovaya   1  Research papers   2  User papers   193  Project/product descriptions  210  Author index    230  iii  Foreword  It  has  been  a  huge  honour  for  me  to  serve  as  president  of  the  European  Association  for  Machine  Translation  (EAMT)  over  the  past  six  years.  As  I  step  down  from  office,  I  am  delighted  that  the  last  EAMT  annual  conference  under  my  presidency  is  being  held  in  the  beautiful location of Antalya, Turkey. This continues the policy I started in 2009 of bringing  EAMT  to  new  regions  of  Europe.  This  began  with  our  first  visit  to  the  Iberian  peninsula  (Barcelona,  2009),  our  first  conference  in  France  in  2010  (St.  Raphael),  followed  by  the  Benelux region in 2011 (Leuven), continuing in 2012 with our first conference hosted in Italy  (Trento), followed by the 2014 meeting in Croatia (Dubrovnik). Quite coincidentally, you may  have  noticed  that  we  have  journeyed  stepbystep  from  West  to  East,  almost  4,000km  in  fact! Just to give you a little hint, next year's conference starts to reverse this trend, but only  just! Of course, you'll have to wait until the closing session of this year's meeting before you  find out the actual 2016 conference location!  The EAMT organised its first Workshop/Conference back in 1996, and now we come to our  Eighteenth Annual Conference in 2015. It is fair to say that for many, our EAMT conferences  are  pencilled  in  long  in  advance  as  nottobe  missed  events.  As  well  as  running  successful  conferences over longer periods of time with much larger numbers of attendees than in the  past,  in  2012  we  ran  the  very  successful  MT  Summit  in  Nice  on  behalf  of  the  whole  MT  community. All these things provide clear evidence to me that the EAMT as an organisation  is continuing to grow and thrive. As I've often noted before, since its inception in 1997, the  EAMT  has  not  raised  its  membership  rates,  and  we  will  continue  to  hold  the  cost  of  membership for 2015. Joining us is great value, especially in years like this when more than  one IAMTaffiliated event takes place: as well as EAMT, we will converge later in the year on  Miami, for MT Summit XV. The close cooperation with the other regional associations, which  started  with  help  from  Alon  Lavie  and  Hitoshi  Isahara  including  mutual  conference  discounts for all IAMT members  continues, despite both AMTA (George Foster) and AAMT  (Hiromi  Nakaiwa)  having  elected  new  presidents.  As  this  is  my  last  conference  as  EAMT  president, I can only hope that this partnership continues and thrives in the future.  As ever, I would like to thank my colleagues on the EAMT Committee. They work tirelessly  on behalf of all of us, and we are truly fortunate to have such a strong body of colleagues  representing  our  Association.  This  year,  there  are  significant  changes  to  your  Committee,  which  we  will  announce  during  the  General  Assembly.  I  urge  all  of  you  to  consider  contributing to this service to the community. I would like to thank all those who have helped  me  on  the  Committee  over  the  past  6  years;  it  is  testament  to  them  all  that  our  Association remains strong, and in good hands for the future.  iv  As in the recent past, I am confident that the programme that has been assembled for this  18th  Conference  is  a  strong  one,  which  will  be  of  great  interest  to  you  all.  I  would  like  to  thank  the  Programme  CoChairs  Felipe  SanchezMartinez  (Research  track)  and  Gema  RamirezSanchez and Fred Hollowood (User track), for their assistance in helping assemble  the programme you have before you, comprising Research and User tracks, poster sessions,  and a terrific Invited Speaker in Olga Beregovaya. As in recent conferences, we continue to  feature  a  special  session  featuring  prominent  FP7/H2020  projects,  which  has  proven  very  popular in the past.   Last  but  not  least,  I  would  especially  like  to  thank  our  local  organizer,  IIknur  Durgar  El Kahlout,  who  very  generously  volunteered  to  hold  the  meeting  in  Antalya.  We  are  very  grateful to Ilknur and her team for their excellent organization of this event.   Finally, thanks to all of you for coming. I hope you all enjoy the conference, that you benefit  from  the  excellent  programme  that  has  been  assembled,  and  that  you  go  away  from  here  having made new friends.  Andy Way  Deputy Director of ADAPT,  School of Computing,  Dublin City University.  President of the EAMT  away@computing.dcu.ie   v  Preface by the Programme Chairs  It  is  our  pleasure  to  welcome  you  to  the  18th  Annual  Conference  of  the  European  Association for Machine Translation (EAMT) to be held in Antalya, Turkey. We really enjoyed  serving  as  a  programme  committee  chairs  for  this  year  edition  of  which  has  become  the  most important event on machine translation in Europe for developers, researchers, users,  professional  translators  and  translation/localisation  managers.  As  in  previous  editions,  the  conference  is  organised  in  three  different  tracks:  a  research  track  in  which  unpublished  research results in machine translation and  related areas are  reported; a user track where  users  of  machine  translation  companies,  language  service  providers,  government  agencies  and nongovernment organisations report their experience on using and adapting machine  translation  in  their  organisations;  and  a  project  and  product  description  track  where  products  and  projects  on  machine  translation  have  the  opportunity  to  reach  the  broad  audience of the conference.  We  received  46  submissions  to  the  research  track,  7  submissions  to  the  user  track  and  20  project/product descriptions. All these papers come from more than 20 different countries.  Each of the research and user papers were peerreviewed by three independent reviewers  from  the  program  committee.  Following  the  reviewers'  suggestion,  one  of  the  papers  submitted to the research track was redirected to the user track; of the remaining 45 papers,  24  (53\%)  were  accepted  for  their  publication  in  the  conference  proceedings:  10  of  them  were  selected  for  oral  presentation,  whereas 14  will  be  presented  as  a  poster.  In  the  user  track 4 papers were accepted (57\%), three of them were selected for oral presentation and  one will be presented as a poster. In the project/product description track 18 papers were  selected for presentation as a poster.   We will enjoy an invited talk by Olga Beregovaya, current Vice President of Language Tools  at Welocalize, who has an extense experience of over 15 years in the localisation industry.  We hope all attendees, researchers and users, will find her talk highly appealing. We will also  have  a  presentation  by  the  winner  of  the  EAMT  Best  Thesis  Award.  Poster  presenters  will  have a twoslides, twominutes presentation of their papers in a poster boaster session.  We  thank  all  the  Programme  Committee  members  and  subreviewers,  whose  names  are  subsequently listed, for their detailed extensive reviews and useful recommendations which  where vital in helping us to decide the papers to accept. We also thank all the authors, who  tried  their  best  to  incorporate  the  reviewers'  suggestions  when  preparing  their  camera ready  papers.  For  those  papers  that  were  not  accepted  we  hope  that  the  reviewers'  comments  will  help  them  to  improve  their  papers  for  their  submission  somewhere  else.  Special  thanks  goes  to  Mikel  L.  Forcada,  who  took  care  of  the  project/product  description  track.  Finally, a big thank you goes to the local organising committee and to all  the authors who  made this conference both possible and successful. We hope that the resulting selection of  papers  represents  the  best  of  machine  translation  research,  development  and  realworld  usage.  Felipe SanchezMartinez  Gema RamirezSanchez  Fred Hollowood  Universitat d'Alacant  Prompsit Language Enginnering  Fred Hollowood Consulting  EAMT 2015 Programme Committee cochairs  vi  Message from the Conference Chair  It  is  my  privilege  and  great  pleasure  to  welcome  you  in  WOW  Topkap  Hotels  for  the  18 th Conference of the European Association for Machine Translation. I am very proud that the  EAMT  conference  is  organized  this  time  in  Antalya,  the  tourism  capital  and  most  beautiful  province of Turkey on the Mediterranean coast.   This year's conference format is the same as those of the last three years, two and half days  of oral and poster sessions, followed by a social programme. I hope you will enjoy the high  quality papers in three different tracks  research, user and product/project  that will give  an overview of current developments and trends in Machine Translation.   The conference will be held at the WOW Topkap Hotel Osmanl Halls. Sessions and coffee  breaks will be hosted in front of the conference room. Lunches will be served in the Hunkar  restaurant  in  a  separated  area  for  EAMT'15  participants.  I  hope  you  will  enjoy  the  social  events  that  we  have  organized:  the  welcome  reception  in  the  Cariye  Pool  and  the  conference  banquet  on  the  beach  of  WOW  Kremlin  Palace.  On  the  last  day  of  the  conference, a cultural tour will be organized to Kursunlu and Perge.  I will have to express my gratitude to the EAMT Board for providing us with the opportunity  to  host the 18 th  EAMT conference; especially Andy Way, Mikel Forcada, Viggo Hansen, and  Tony Clarke who helped me whenever needed. It was a great pleasure to work with you. I  would like to thank the Program  Chair, Felipe SanchezMartinez,  and User Cochairs Gema  RamirezSanchez and Fred Hollowood for taking care of the large number of submissions and  for preparing the programme.   This  conference  would  not  be  possible  without  the  efforts  of  many  people  involved  in  its  organization;  our  organizational  partner  DEKON  particularly  Kubilay  Sahin  and  Kubra  Senkahveci  who  worked  hard  to  prepare  a  successful  setup  for  the  conference,  local  organization cochair Mehmed Ozkan and our local organization committee members Kemal  Oflazer, Coskun Mermer, Yucel Bicil, Seniz Demir and Alper Kanak who volunteered for the  organization and helped during every stage of the preparations.   Lastly,  I  am  grateful  to  our  sponsors  for  their  generous  contributions;  gold  sponsor  STAR,  bronze sponsors KuveytTurk, Ebay, and Universal, Welcome Reception Sponsor SesTek and  lastly lunch sponsor Welocalize.   I  wish  you  a  very  successful  18 th EAMT  conference  in  Antalya.  Enjoy  both  the  academic  program and Antalya during your stay!  Ilknur Durgar ElKahlout  TUBITAKBILGEM  ilknur.durgar@tubitak.gov.tr   vii  EAMT 2015 Committees   </chunk></section><section><heading>Chairs   </heading><chunk>General Chair of the Conference: Andy Way  (Dublin City University, Ireland)   Research Programme Chair: Felipe SanchezMartinez  (Universitat dAlacant, Spain)   User Programme Cochair: Gema RamirezSanchez  (Prompsit Language Engineering, Spain)   User Programme Cochair: Fred Hollowood  (Fred Hollowood Consulting, Ireland)   Local Organization Cochair: Mehmed Ozkan (Bogazici University)   Local Organization Cochair: Ilknur Durgar ElKahlout (TUBITAKBILGEM)   Local Organizing Committee   Kemal Oflazer (CMU Qatar)   Coskun Mermer (TUBITAKBILGEM)   Yucel Bicil (TUBITAKBILGEM)   Seniz Demir (TUBITAKBILGEM)   Alper Kanak (TUBITAKBILGEM)   Research Committee   Jesus AndresFerrer (Nuance Communications, USA)   Eleftherios Avramidis (German Research Center for Artificial Intelligence (DFKI), Germany)   Bogdan Babych (University of Leeds, UK)   Loic Barrault (Universite du Maine, France)   Nuria Bel (Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Spain)   Nicola Bertoldi (Fondazione Bruno Kessler, Italy)   Laurent Besacier (Universite J. Fourier, France)   Alexandra Birch (University of Edinburgh, UK)   Arianna Bisazza (University of Amsterdam, Netherlands)   Herve Blanchon (Laboratoire dInformatique de Grenoble, France)   Ondrej Bojar (Charles University in Prague, Czech Republic)   Nicola Cancedda (Applied Researcher at Microsoft, UK)   Michael Carl (Copenhagen Business School, Denmark)   Francisco Casacuberta (Universitat Politecnica de Valencia, Spain)   Helena Caseli (Universidade Federal de Sao Carlos, Brazil)   Mauro Cettolo (Fondazione Bruno Kessler, Italy)   David Chiang (University of Notre Dame, USA)   Marta R. CostaJussa (Institute For Infocomm Research, Singapore)   Adria De Gispert (University of Cambridge, UK)   Jinhua Du (Xian University of Technology, China)   Nadir Durrani (University of Edinburgh, UK)   Marc Dymetman (Xerox Research Centre Europe, France)   Andreas Eisele (DirectorateGeneral for Translation (EC), Luxembourg)   Cristina EspanaBonet (Universitat Politecnica de Catalunya, Spain)   Mireia Farrus (Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Spain)   Christian Federmann (Microsoft, USA)   Mark Fishel (University of Zurich, Switzerland)  Mikel L. Forcada (Universitat dAlacant, Spain)   viii  George Foster (National Research Council, Canada)   Federico Gaspari (Dublin City University, Ireland)   Ulrich Germann (University of Edinburgh, UK)   Jesus Gimenez (Nuance Communications, USA)   Meritxell Gonzalez (Universitat Politecnica de Catalunya, Spain)   Barry Haddow (University of Edinburgh, UK)   Christian Hardmeier (University of Uppsala, Sweden)   Yifan He (New York University, USA)   Kenneth Heafield (Bloomberg Labs, USA)   Teresa Herrmann (Karlsruhe Institute of Technology, Germany)   Hieu Hoang (University of Edinburgh, UK)   Matthias Huck (University of Edinburgh, UK)   Gonzalo Iglesias (University of Cambridge, UK)   Jie Jiang (Applied Language Solutions, UK)   Marcin JunczysDowmunt (Adam Mickiewicz University, Poland)   Philipp Koehn (John Hopkins University, USA)   Roland Kuhn (National Research Council, Canada)   Alon Lavie (Carnegie Mellon University, USA)   Qun Liu (Dublin City University, Ireland; Chinese Academy of Sciences, China)   Yanjun Ma (Baidu, China)   Pavel Pecina (Charles University in Prague, Czech Republic)   Juan Antonio PerezOrtiz (Universitat dAlacant, Spain)   Maja Popovic (German Research Center for Artificial Intelligence (DFKI), Germany)   Stefan Riezler (Heidelberg University, Germany)   Mike Rosner (University of Malta, Malta)   Raphael Rubino (Prompsit Language Engineering, Spain)   Kepa Sarasola (Euskal Herriko Unibertsitatea, Spain)   Lane Schwartz (University of Illinois, USA)   Holger Schwenk (University of Le Mans, France)   Kashif Shah (University of Sheffield, UK)   Khalil Simaan (University of Amsterdam, Netherlands)   Michel Simard (National Research Council, Canada)   Lucia Specia (University of Sheffield, UK)   Ankit Srivastava (Dublin City University, Ireland)   Sara Stymne (Uppsala University, Sweden)   Jorg Tiedemann (Uppsala University, Sweden)   Antonio Toral (Dublin City University, Ireland)   Dan Tufis (Academia Romana, Romania)   Marco Turchi (Fondazione Bruno Kessler, Italy)   Francis M. Tyers (UiT Norgga arktala universitehta, Norway)   Antal van Den Bosch (Radboud University Nijmegen, Netherlands)   Josef van Genabith (German Research Center for Artificial Intelligence (DFKI), Germany)  Vincent Vandeghinste (University of Leuven, Belgium)  David Vilar (Nuance Communications, USA)  Martin Volk (University of Zurich, Switzerland)  Andy Way (Dublin City University, Ireland)  ix  Jurgen Wedekind (University of Copenhagen, Denmark)  Francois Yvon (Universite Paris Sud, France)  User Committee  Jeff Allen (SaP, France)  Nora Aranberri (Euskal Herriko Uni, Spain)  Diego Bartolome (Tauyou, Spain)  Olga Beregovata (Welocalise, US)  Eric Blassin (Lionbridge, France)  Arancha Caballero (Nuadda, Spain)  James Cogley (Microsoft, Ireland)  Arnaud Daix (Euroscript, Luxembourg)  Pedro Diez (Linguaserve, Spain)  Stephen Doherty (UNSW, Australia)  Kurt Eberle (Lingenio, Germany)  Wojceich Froelich (Argos, Poland)  Tatiana Gornostay (Tilde, Latvia)  Declan Groves (Microsoft, Ireland)  Manuel Herranz (Pangeanic, Spain)  Maxim Khalilov (bmmt, Germany)  Paul Mangell (alphacrc, UK)  Jay Marciano (Lionbridge, US)  Daniel Marcu (Uni Southern Calif, US)  John Moran (CNGL, Ireland)  Hideyuki Namiki (Sony, Japan)  Antoni Oliver (UOC, Spain)  Patricia Palidini (CA, Spain)  John Papaioannou (Lexcelera, France)  Niko Papula (Multilizer, Findland)  Mirko Plitt (Modulo Language Automation, Switzerland)  Phil Ritchie (Vistatec, Ireland)  Johann Roturier (Symantec, Ireland)  Javier Sastre (Ateknea Solutions, Spain)  Indra Semite (Tilde, Latvia)  Jean Senellart (Systran, France)  Pilos Spyridon (EC, Belgium)  Ventsislav Zhechev (Autodesk, Switzerland)  </chunk></section><section><heading>SubReviewers   </heading><chunk>Sariya Karimova (Heidelberg University, Germany)  Arefeh Kazemi (University of Isfahan, Iran)  Gideon Maillette de Buij Wenninger (University of Amsterdam, Netherlands)  Carolina Scarton (University of Sheffield, UK)  Maarten van Gompel (Radboud University Nijmegen, Netherlands)  Longyue Wang (University of Macau, China)  x  xi  List of papers  Invited Talk  What we want, what we need, what we absolutely cant do without  an enterprise users   perspective on machine translation technology and stuff around it  Olga Beregovaya  1  Research papers  2  Exploiting portability to build an RBMT prototype for a new source language  Nora Aranberri, Gorka Labaka, Arantza Diaz de Ilarraza and Kepa Sarasola  3  Building hybrid machine translation systems by using an EBMT preprocessor   to create partialtranslations  Mikel Artetxe, Gorka Labaka, Kepa Sarasola  11  Using online available sources of bilingual information for wordlevel   machine translation quality estimation  Miquel EsplaGomis, Felipe SanchezMartinez, Mikel L. Forcada  19  A general framework for minimizing translation effort: towards a principled   combination of translation technologies in computeraided translation  Mikel L. Forcada and Felipe SanchezMartinez  27  Can Translation Memories afford not to use paraphrasing?  Rohit Gupta, Constantin Orasan, Marcos Zampieri, Mihaela Vela, Josef van Genabith  35  Dependencybased Reordering Model for Constituent Pairs in Hierarchical SMT  Arefeh Kazemiy, Antonio Toral, Andy Way, Amirhassan Monadjemiy,   Mohammadali Nematbakhshy  43 The role of artificially generated negative data for quality estimation of   machine translation  Varvara Logacheva and Lucia Specia   51  DocumentLevel Machine Translation with Word Vector Models  Eva Martinez Garcia, Cristina EspanaBonet, Lluis Marquez  59  The potential and limits of lay postediting in an online community  Linda Mitchell   67  PostEditing Evaluations: Tradeoffs between Novice and Professional Participants  Joss Moorkens and Sharon OBrien  75  Benchmarking SMT Performance for Farsi Using the TEP++ Corpus  Peyman Passban, Andy Way, Qun Liu  82  xii  Dynamic Terminology Integration Methods in Statistical Machine Translation  Marcis Pinnis  89  Identifying main obstacles for statistical machine translation of   morphologically rich South Slavic languages  Maja Popovic and Mihael Arcan  97  Poor mans lemmatisation for automatic error classification  Maja Popovic, Mihael Arcan, Eleftherios Avramidis, Aljoscha Burchardt,  Arle Lommel  105  Truly Exploring Multiple References for Machine Translation Evaluation  Ying Qin and Lucia Specia  113  Searching for Context: a Study on DocumentLevel Labels   for Translation Quality Estimation  Carolina Scarton, Marcos Zampieri, Mihaela Vela, Josef van Genabith, Lucia Specia  121  Stripping Adjectives: Integration Techniques for   Selective Stemming in SMT Systems  Isabel Slawik, Jan Niehues, Alex Waibel  129  Evaluating machine translation for assimilation via a gapfilling task  Ekaterina Ageeva, Francis M. Tyers, Mikel L. Forcada, Juan Antonio PerezOrtiz  137  Unsupervised training of maximumentropy models for lexical selection   in rulebased machine translation  Francis M. Tyers, Felipe SanchezMartinez, Mikel L. Forcada  145  Assessing linguistically aware fuzzy matching in translation memories  Tom Vanallemeersch and Vincent Vandeghinste  153  Reassessingthe WMT2013 Human Evaluation with Professional Translators Trainees  Mihaela Vela and Josef van Genabith  161  Integrating a Large, Monolingual Corpus as Translation Memory into   Statistical Machine translation  Katharina Waschle and Stefan Riezler  169  TargetSide Generation of Prepositions for SMT  Marion Weller, Alexander Fraser, Sabine Schulte im Walde  177  Word Alignment Based Parallel Corpora Evaluation  and Cleaning Using Machine Learning Techniques  Ieva Zarina, Peteris Nikiforovs, Raivis Skadin  185  xiii  User papers  193  Content Translation: Computerassisted translation   tool for Wikipedia articles  Niklas Laxstrom, Pau Giner, Santhosh Thottingal  194  Prereordering for Statistical Machine Translation of Nonfictional Subtitles.  Magdalena Plamada, Gion Linder, Phillip Strobel, Martin Volk  198  SMT at the International Maritime Organization:   experiences with combining inhouse corpus with more general corpus  Bruno Pouliquen, Marcin JunczysDowmunt, Blanca Pinero, Micha Ziemski  202  Evaluation of the domain adaptation of MT systems in ACCURAT  Gregor Thurmair  206  Project/product descriptions  210  MixedEmotions: Social Semantic Emotion Analysis for Innovative Multilingual   Big Data Analytics Markets  Mihael Arcan and Paul Buitelaar  211  The ACCEPT Academic Portal: Bringing Together Preediting, MT and   Postediting into a Learning Environment  Pierrette Bouillon, Johanna Gerlach, Asheesh Gulati, Victoria Porro, Violeta Seretan  212  RussianChinese Sentencelevel Aligned News Corpus   Wenjun Du, Wuying Liu, Junting Yu, Mianzhu Yi  213  HimL (Health in my Language)  Barry Haddow   214  MTenhanced fuzzy matching with Transit NXT and STAR Moses  Nadira Hofmann  215  HandyCAT  An OpenSource Platform for CAT Tool Research  Chris Hokamp and Qun Liu  216  TraMOOC: Translation for Massive Open Online Courses  Valia Kordoni, Kostadin Cholakov, Markus Egg, Andy Way, Lexi Birch, Katia Kermanidis,  Vilelmini Sosoni, Dimitrios Tsoumakos, Antal van den Bosch, Iris Hendrickx, Michael  Papadopoulos, Panayota Georgakopoulou, Maria Gialama, Menno van Zaanen,   Ioana Buliga, Mitja Jermol and Davor Orlic  217  Streamlining Translation Workflows with Style Scorer  David Landan and Olga Beregovaya  218  xiv  EstonianEnglish Reversible Smart Phone Dictionary of   Military Terms and Relevant Vocabulary  Epp Leete  219  FALCON: Federated Active Linguistic data CuratiON  David Lewis  220  Tapadoir  Eimear Maguire, John Judge and Teresa Lynn  221  Okapi+QuEst: Translation Quality Estimation within Okapi  Gustavo Henrique Paetzold, Lucia Specia, Yves Savourel  222  CRACKER: Cracking the Language Barrier  Georg Rehm  223  LTC KnowHow: Empowering the Social Enterprise in the Language Industry  Adriane Rinsche and Sabine Rinsches  224  MultiDialect Machine Translation (MuDMat)  Fatiha Sadat  226  AbuMaTran: Automatic building of Machine Translation  Antonio Toral, Tommi A Pirinen, Andy Way, Gema RamirezSanchez,   Sergio Ortiz Rojas, Raphael Rubino, Miquel Espla, Mikel Forcada,   Vassilis Papavassiliou, Prokopis Prokopidis and Nikola Ljubeic  227  MNHTT: A Platform to Support Collaborative Translator Training  Masao Utiyama, Kyo Kageura, Martin Thomas, Anthony Hartley  228  Smart Computer Aided Translation Environment  Vincent Vandeghinste, Tom Vanallemeersch, Frank Van Eynde, Geert Heyman,   Sien Moens, Joris Pelemans, Patrick Wambacq, Iulianna Van der Lek  Ciudin,   Arda Tezcan, Lieve Macken, Veronique Hoste, Eva Geurts and Mieke Haesen  229  Invited Talk  Olga Beregovaya  What we want, what we need, what we absolutely cant do without  an  enterprise users perspective on machine translation technology and  stuff around it  As  the  gains  made  by  current  phrasebased  MT  systems  approach  a  horizontal  asymptote,  those of us in industry who benefit from cuttingedge research are giving serious thought to  whats  next.  The  goal  of  this  talk  is  to  rekindle  the  dialog  between  research  and  industry  circles  on  the  immediate  and  future  needs  of  the  user  community  and  finding  mutually  beneficial and interesting avenues for collaboration.   Of course, there are too many topics to cover in an hour, but Ill try to touch on some of the  most relevant  These are the areas of utmost interest and importance for the global business community as  seen by a user from a major Language Service Provider:  Translation Quality: Its clear that weve nearly hit the wall with what more we can squeeze  out  of  phrasebased  MT  systems,  so  where  do  we  go  from  here?  Are  factored models  the  way to go, or should we in industry start giving serious consideration to systems using deep  learning techniques and/or deep syntactic/semantic structures?  New  reallife  applications:  Usergenerated  content  (UGC)  is  rapidly  becoming  a  huge  opportunity  for  translation  &amp;  localization.  Whether  were  talking  about  blogs,  reviews,  or  live  chat,  there  are  challenges  for  the  MT  status  quo:  normalization,  ungrammatical/uncommon  syntax,  extreme  sensitivity  to  maintaining  proper  negation  or  sentiment.  Domain adaptation: How much can we get out of minimal amounts of data? A little more  data? Lots of outofdomain data? How can we seamlessly integrate client/user dictionaries  into standard SMT workflows?  Using  and  interpreting  metadata:  Were  seeing  a  trend  where  we  often  have  as  much  or  more metadata than actual text to translate. How can this be leveraged to improve results,  and make translators/posteditors lives easier?  Quality  evaluation,  utility  prediction:  What  do  we  even  mean  by  utility?  Lets  work  together  on  establishing  a  standard.  Can  we  get  robust,  reliable  QE  from  limited  (or  no)  bilingual data? (Weve got some evidence that the answer is yes) What can we say about  quality vis a vis functionality?  Collaboration:  We  want  to  help!  Were  very  interested  to  see  research  thats  directly  applicable,  and  we  want to  find  ways  to  facilitate  academic/industry  partnerships.  We  can  work with clients to try to make large amounts of domainspecific (nonparliamentary!) data  available. Please reach out to us so we know what youre working on. Better yet, lets work  on finding mutually beneficial projects.  1 </chunk></section></sec_map>