<sec_map><section><chunk>BSNLP 2015 The 5th Workshop on Balto-Slavic Natural Language Processing Sponsored by SIGSLAV Proceedings of the Workshop associated with The 10th International Conference on Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing (RANLP 2015) 1011 September 2015 Hissar, Bulgaria The 5th Workshop on Balto-Slavic Natural Language Processing associated with THE INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE RECENT ADVANCES IN NATURAL LANGUAGE PROCESSING 2015 PROCEEDINGS Hissar, Bulgaria 1011 September 2015 ISBN 978-954-452-033-5 Designed and Printed by INCOMA Ltd. Shoumen, BULGARIA ii Preface This volume contains the papers presented at BSNLP 2015: the fifth in a series of Workshops on Balto- Slavic Natural Language Processing. This BSNLP Workshop is the first endorsed by SIGSLAVthe newly established ACL Special Interest Group on Natural Language Processing in Slavic Languages. 1 The driving motivation behind convening the BSNLP Workshops is twofold. On one hand, the languages from the Balto-Slavic group are important for NLP due to their widespread use and diverse cultural heritage. They are spoken by over 400 million speakers worldwide. Due to the recent political and economic developments in Central and Eastern Europe, the countries where Balto-Slavic languages are spoken were brought into new focus in terms of rapid technological advancement and rapidly expanding consumer markets. In the context of the European Union, the Balto-Slavic group today covers about one third of all speakers of EUs official languages. On the other hand, research on theoretical and applied NLP in many of the Balto-Slavic languages is still in its early stages, although it is continually progressing. The advent of the Internet over twenty years ago established the dominant role of English in a broad range of on-line activities, which further weakened the position of other languages, including the Balto-Slavic group. Consequently, as compared to English, there is still a lack of resources, processing tools and applications for most of these languages, especially ones with smaller speaker bases. Despite this minority status, the Balto-Slavic languages offer a wealth of fascinating scientific and technical challenges for researchers and practitioners to work on. The linguistic phenomena specific to Balto-Slavic languagessuch as rich morphological inflection and relatively free word orderpresent highly intriguing and non-trivial challenges to building NLP tools, and require richer morphological and syntactic resources. Related to this theme, the invited talk by Tanja Samardzic, titled A computational cross-linguistic approach to Slavic verb aspect discusses challenges encountered in the computational treatment of the complex phenomena related to verbal aspect in Slavic languages. The talk presents how fine-grained aspectual classes can be automatically extracted using parallel corpora, and then used in temporal classification of events across languages. In the second invited talk, titled Challenges in launching an NLP start-up company: Research meets the Real World, Josef Steinberger discusses his experience in transferring research results related to Slavic languages into commercial products. The main goal of the BSNLP 2015 Workshop is to bring together all related stakeholders, including academic researchers and industry practitioners who are involved in work on NLP for Balto-Slavic languages. The Workshop aims to further stimulate research on NLP for these languages and to foster the creation and dissemination of relevant tools and resources. The Workshop serves as an interactive platform for researchers to exchange ideas and experiences, discuss difficult and shared problems, and to facilitate making new resources more widely-known. This Workshop continues the proud tradition established by the previous BSNLP Workshops: 1. the First BSNLP Workshop, held in conjunction with ACL 2007 Conference in Prague, Czech Republic; 2. the Second BSNLP Workshop, held in conjunction with IIS 2009: Intelligent Information Systems, in Krakow, Poland; 3. the Third BSNLP Workshop, held in conjunction with TSD 2011, 14th International Conference on Text, Speech and Dialogue in Plze n, Czech Republic; 1 http://sigslav.cs.helsinki.fi/ iii 4. the Fourth BSNLP Workshop, held in conjunction with ACL 2007 Conference in Sofia, Bulgaria. This year we received 29 submissions, out of which 16 were accepted for presentation: 13 as regular papers and three as interactive presentations (resulting in an overall acceptance rate of 55%). Compared to previous BSNLP workshops, this year we have a mixed balance of papers on enabling technologies and higher-level tasks, such as information extraction, sentiment analysis and text classification. This shows the ongoing trend towards building user-oriented applications for Balto-Slavic languages, in addition to working on lower-level NLP tools. The papers directly deal with at least seven Balto-Slavic languages: Bulgarian, Croatian, Czech, Lithuanian, Polish, Russian, and Serbian. Three of the papers discuss approaches to syntactic and semantic analysis. Three papers are about information extraction. Three papers cover sentiment analysis and text classification. Other papers address a broad range of topics, including word-sense disambiguation, corpus analysis, text and author modeling, and linguistic resources. It is our sincere hope that this work will help to further strengthen the community and stimulate the growth of research in this rich and exciting field. BSNLP Organizers: Jakub Piskorski (Polish Academy of Sciences) Lidia Pivovarova (University of Helsinki) Jan Snajder (University of Zagreb) Hristo Tanev (Joint Research Centre) Roman Yangarber (University of Helsinki) iv Organizers: Jakub Piskorski, Polish Academy of Sciences, Poland Lidia Pivovarova, University of Helsinki, Finland Jan Snajder, University of Zagreb, Croatia Hristo Tanev, Joint Research Centre of the European Commission, Ispra, Italy Roman Yangarber, University of Helsinki, Finland Program Committee: Zeljko Agi  c, University of Copenhagen, Denmark Tomaz Erjavec, Jozef Stefan Institute, Slovenia Darja Fiser, University of Ljubljana, Slovenia Radovan Garabik, Comenius University in Bratislava, Slovakia Maxim Gubin, Facebook Inc., Menlo Park CA, USA Tomas Krilavi cius, Vytautas Magnus University, Kaunas, Lithuania Vladislav Kubo n, Charles University, Prague, Czech Republic Natalia Loukachevitch, Moscow State University, Russia Preslav Nakov, Qatar Computing Research Institute, Qatar Petya Osenova, Bulgarian Academy of Sciences, Bulgaria Karel Pala, Masaryk University, Brno, Czech Republic Maciej Piasecki, Wrocaw University of Technology, Poland Jakub Piskorski, Polish Academy of Sciences, Warsaw, Poland Lidia Pivovarova, University of Helsinki, Finland Tanja Samardzi  c, University of Zurich, Switzerland Agata Savary, University of Tours, France Kiril Simov, Bulgarian Academy of Sciences, Bulgaria Inguna Skadina, University of Latvia, Latvia Jan Snajder, University of Zagreb, Croatia Josef Steinberger, University of West Bohemia, Czech Republic Stan Szpakowicz, University of Ottawa, Canada Marko Tadi  c, University of Zagreb, Croatia Hristo Tanev, Joint Research Centre, Italy Irina Temnikova, Qatar Computing Research Institute, Qatar Marcin Woli  nski, Polish Academy of Sciences, Warsaw, Poland Roman Yangarber, University of Helsinki, Finland Invited Speakers: Tanja Samardzi  c, University of Zurich, Switzerland Josef Steinberger, University of West Bohemia, Czech Republic v Table of Contents Universal Dependencies for Croatian (that work for Serbian, too) Zeljko Agi  c and Nikola Ljubesi  c . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1 Analytic Morphology Merging the Paradigmatic and Syntagmatic Perspective in a Treebank Vladimir Petkevi c, Alexandr Rosen, Hana Skoumalova and P remysl Vitovec . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9 Resolving Entity Coreference in Croatian with a Constrained Mention-Pair Model Goran Glavas and Jan Snajder . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 17 Evaluation of Coreference Resolution Tools for Polish from the Information Extraction Perspective Adam Kaczmarek and Micha Marci  nczuk . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 24 Open Relation Extraction for Polish: Preliminary Experiments Jakub Piskorski . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 34 Regional Linguistic Data Initiative (ReLDI) Tanja Samardzi  c, Nikola Ljubesi  c and Maja Mili cevi  c . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 40 Online Extraction of Russian Multiword Expressions Mikhail Kopotev, Llorenc Escoter, Daria Kormacheva, Matthew Pierce, Lidia Pivovarova and Ro- man Yangarber . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 43 E-law Module Supporting Lawyers in the Process of Knowledge Discovery from Legal Documents Marek Kozowski, Maciej Kowalski and Maciej Kazula. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .46 Experiments on Active Learning for Croatian Word Sense Disambiguation Domagoj Alagi  c and Jan Snajder . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 49 Automatic Classification of WordNet Morphosemantic Relations Svetlozara Leseva, Ivelina Stoyanova, Maria Todorova, Tsvetana Dimitrova, Borislav Rizov and Svetla Koeva . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 59 Applying Multi-Dimensional Analysis to a Russian Webcorpus: Searching for Evidence of Genres Anisya Katinskaya and Serge Sharoff . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 65 Distinctive Similarity of Clausal Coordinate Ellipsis in Russian Compared to Dutch, Estonian, German, and Hungarian Karin Harbusch and Denis Krusko . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 75 Universalizing BulTreeBank: a Linguistic Tale about Glocalization Petya Osenova and Kiril Simov . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 81 Types of Aspect Terms in Aspect-Oriented Sentiment Labeling Natalia Loukachevitch, Evgeniy Kotelnikov and Pavel Blinov . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 90 Authorship Attribution and Author Profiling of Lithuanian Literary Texts Jurgita Kapo ci  ut  e-Dzikien  e, Andrius Utka and Ligita Sarkut  e . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 96 Classification of Short Legal Lithuanian Texts Vytautas Mickevi cius, Tomas Krilavi cius and Vaidas Morkevi cius . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 106 vii Workshop Program Thursday, September 10, 2015 09:0009:10 Welcoming Remarks: BSNLP Organizers 09:1010:00 Invited Talk A Computational Cross-Linguistic Approach to Slavic Verb Aspect Tanja Samardzi  c 10:1011:00 Session I: Syntax 10:1010:35 Universal Dependencies for Croatian (that work for Serbian, too) Zeljko Agi  c and Nikola Ljubesi  c 10:3511:00 Analytic Morphology Merging the Paradigmatic and Syntagmatic Perspective in a Treebank Vladimir Petkevi c, Alexandr Rosen, Hana Skoumalova and P remysl Vitovec 11:0011:30 Coffee Break 11:3012:35 Session II: Information Extraction 11:3011:50 Resolving Entity Coreference in Croatian with a Constrained Mention-Pair Model Goran Glavas and Jan Snajder 11:5012:15 Evaluation of Coreference Resolution Tools for Polish from the Information Extrac- tion Perspective Adam Kaczmarek and Micha Marci  nczuk 12:1512:35 Open Relation Extraction for Polish: Preliminary Experiments Jakub Piskorski ix Thursday, September 10, 2015 (continued) 12:3514:00 Lunch 14:0014:50 Invited Talk Challenges in Launching an NLP Start-up Company: Research Meets the Real World Josef Steinberger 15:0015:30 Interactive Session 15:0015:10 Regional Linguistic Data Initiative (ReLDI) Tanja Samardzi  c, Nikola Ljubesi  c and Maja Mili cevi  c 15:1015:20 Online Extraction of Russian Multiword Expressions Mikhail Kopotev, Llorenc Escoter, Daria Kormacheva, Matthew Pierce, Lidia Pivo- varova and Roman Yangarber 15:2015:30 E-law Module Supporting Lawyers in the Process of Knowledge Discovery from Legal Documents Marek Kozowski, Maciej Kowalski and Maciej Kazula 15:3016:00 Coffee Break 16:0017:00 Discussion on BSNLP/SIGSLAV Activities: Shared NLP Task x Friday, September 11, 2015 09:0009:45 Session III: Semantics 09:0009:25 Experiments on Active Learning for Croatian Word Sense Disambiguation Domagoj Alagi  c and Jan Snajder 09:2509:45 Automatic Classification of WordNet Morphosemantic Relations Svetlozara Leseva, Ivelina Stoyanova, Maria Todorova, Tsvetana Dimitrova, Borislav Rizov and Svetla Koeva 09:5511:00 Session IV: Corpus Analysis and Resources 09:5510:20 Applying Multi-Dimensional Analysis to a Russian Webcorpus: Searching for Evi- dence of Genres Anisya Katinskaya and Serge Sharoff 10:2010:40 Distinctive Similarity of Clausal Coordinate Ellipsis in Russian Compared to Dutch, Estonian, German, and Hungarian Karin Harbusch and Denis Krusko 10:4011:00 Universalizing BulTreeBank: a Linguistic Tale about Glocalization Petya Osenova and Kiril Simov 11:0011:30 Coffee Break xi Friday, September 11, 2015 (continued) 11:3012:35 Session V: Sentiment Analysis and Text Classification 11:3011:50 Types of Aspect Terms in Aspect-Oriented Sentiment Labeling Natalia Loukachevitch, Evgeniy Kotelnikov and Pavel Blinov 11:5012:15 Authorship Attribution and Author Profiling of Lithuanian Literary Texts Jurgita Kapo ci  ut  e-Dzikien  e, Andrius Utka and Ligita Sarkut  e 12:1512:35 Classification of Short Legal Lithuanian Texts Vytautas Mickevi cius, Tomas Krilavi cius and Vaidas Morkevi cius 12:3512:40 Closing Remarks 12:4014:00 Lunch xii </chunk></section></sec_map>