<sec_map><section><chunk>ACL-IJCNLP 2015 The 53rd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics and the 7th International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing Proceedings of the Grammar Engineering Across Frameworks (GEAF) Workshop July 30, 2015 Beijing, China Production and Manufacturing by Taberg Media Group AB Box 94, 562 02 Taberg Sweden c 2015 The Association for Computational Linguistics Order print-on-demand copies from: Curran Associates 57 Morehouse Lane Red Hook, New York 12571 USA Tel: +1-845-758-0400 Fax: +1-845-758-2633 curran@proceedings.com ISBN 978-1-932432-66-4 / 1-932432-66-3 (Volume 1) ISBN 978-1-932432-67-1 / 1-932432-67-1 (Volume 2) ii Introduction Grammar Engineering Across Frameworks (GEAF) 2015 took place on 30 July 2015 in Beijing. This workshop builds on several previous workshop on the same topic, namely GEAF 2007 at the LSA Linguistic Institute at Stanford, GEAF 2008 at COLING in Manchester, GEAF 2009 at ACL/IJCNLP in Singapore and HMGE 2013 at ESSLLI 2013 in Dusseldorf. Grammar engineering, the practice of developing linguistically motivated grammars in software, is an active area of research in computational linguistics and comprises contemporary works across many different theoretical frameworks. The fruits of grammar engineering, namely linguistically motivated grammars which in many cases provide rich, detailed semantic representations, support the development of natural language technologies, including both natural language understanding and generation, that derive much more information from the linguistic signal than is otherwise possible. The goal of this workshop is to bring together researchers working in grammar engineering and to advance the state of the art in this field. In addition to the nine papers included in these proceedings, the workshop featured a panel discussion on how grammar engineering can continue to be relevant in computational linguistics. The panel addressed questions such as, What are the strengths of grammars that cannot be ignored? What success stories do we have? What should be done differently? And what can we learn from other approaches? We are grateful to the program committee for their thoughtful comments on the submitted papers and to the authors and panelists for valuable contributions to the study of grammar engineering. Emily M. Bender, Lori Levin, Stefan Muller, Yannick Parmentier, and Aarne Ranta iii Organizers: Emily M. Bender (U Washington) (Chair) Lori Levin (Carnegie Mellon University) Stefan Muller (FU Berlin) Yannick Parmentier (U Orleans) Aarne Ranta (U Goteborg) Program Committee: Krasimir Angelov (U Goteborg) Pushpak Bhattacharyya (IIT Bombay) Philippe Blache (CNRS) Miriam Butt (U Konstanz) Robin Cooper (U Goteborg) Berthold Crysmann (CNRS) Eric De La Clergerie (Paris 7) Ramona Enache (U Goteborg) Dan Flickinger (Stanford) Antske Fokkens (VU Amsterdam) Claire Gardent (CNRS) Sylvain Kahane (U Paris Ouest) Tracy King (eBay) Anna Kups  c (U Bordeaux) Hans Leiss (LMU Munich) Timm Lichte (U Dusseldorf) Detmar Meurers (U Tubingen) Richard Moot (CNRS) Glyn Morrill (UPC Barcelona) Guy Perrier (U Lorraine) Adam Przepiorkowski (PAS) Frank Richter (U Frankfurt) Sanghoun Song (NTU) Francis Tyers (U Troms) Christina Unger (U Bielefeld) Gertjan van Noord (U Groeningen) v Table of Contents Grammar Engineering for a Customer: a Case Study with Five Languages Aarne Ranta, Christina Unger and Daniel Vidal Hussey . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1 Building an HPSG-based Indonesian Resource Grammar (INDRA) David Moeljadi, Francis Bond and Sanghoun Song . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 9 An HPSG-based Shared-Grammar for the Chinese Languages: ZHONG [|] Zhenzhen Fan, Sanghoun Song and Francis Bond . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 17 Parsing Chinese with a Generalized Categorial Grammar Manjuan Duan and William Schuler . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 25 Orthography Engineering in Grammatical Framework Krasimir Angelov . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 33 A Cloud-Based Editor for Multilingual Grammars Thomas Hallgren, Ramona Enache and Aarne Ranta . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 41 Formalising the Swedish Constructicon in Grammatical Framework Normunds Gruzitis, Dana Dannells, Benjamin Lyngfelt and Aarne Ranta . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 49 Representing Honorifics via Individual Constraints Sanghoun Song . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 57 Resumption and Extraction in an Implemented HPSG of Hausa Berthold Crysmann . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 65 vii Workshop Program Thursday, July 30, 2015 9:159:30 Opening session 9:3010:30 Session 1 09:3010:00 Grammar Engineering for a Customer: a Case Study with Five Languages Aarne Ranta, Christina Unger and Daniel Vidal Hussey 10:0010:30 Building an HPSG-based Indonesian Resource Grammar (INDRA) David Moeljadi, Francis Bond and Sanghoun Song 10:3011:00 Coffee break 11:0012:30 Session 2 11:0011:30 An HPSG-based Shared-Grammar for the Chinese Languages: ZHONG [|] Zhenzhen Fan, Sanghoun Song and Francis Bond 11:3012:00 Parsing Chinese with a Generalized Categorial Grammar Manjuan Duan and William Schuler 12:0012:30 Orthography Engineering in Grammatical Framework Krasimir Angelov 12:3014:00 Lunch break ix Thursday, July 30, 2015 (continued) 14:0015:30 Session 3 14:0014:30 A Cloud-Based Editor for Multilingual Grammars Thomas Hallgren, Ramona Enache and Aarne Ranta 14:3015:00 Formalising the Swedish Constructicon in Grammatical Framework Normunds Gruzitis, Dana Dannells, Benjamin Lyngfelt and Aarne Ranta 15:0015:30 Representing Honorifics via Individual Constraints Sanghoun Song 15:3016:00 Coffee break 16:0018:00 Session 4 16:0016:30 Resumption and Extraction in an Implemented HPSG of Hausa Berthold Crysmann 16:4518:00 Panel discussion: the future of grammar engineering x </chunk></section></sec_map>