<sec_map><section><chunk>Extended Tree Transducers in Natural Language Processing Andreas Maletti Institut for Natural Language Processing, Universit  at Stuttgart Pfaffenwaldring 5b, 70569 Stuttgart, Germany maletti@ims.uni-stuttgart.de Extended Abstract Tree transducers are finite-state devices comput- ing relations on trees. Their study was initiated by Thatcher (1970) and Rounds (1970), who es- tablished the classical top-down tree transducers that process the input tree from the root towards the leaves. Shortly afterwards, Baker (1973) in- troduced the bottom-up tree transducers that pro- cess the input tree from the leaves towards the root in analogy to the top-down and bottom-up tree automata (Thatcher, 1973). Due to applications in syntax-directed semantics (F  ul  op and Vogler, 1998), tree transducers were extensively studied in the following years as detailed in (G  ecseg and Steinby, 1984) and (G  ecseg and Steinby, 1997). Notable extensions to the original top-down tree transducers include the top-down tree transduc- ers with regular look-ahead by Engelfriet (1977), the attributed tree transducers of F  ul  op (1981), and the macro tree transducers by Courcelle and Franchi-Zannettacci (1982) and Engelfriet and Vogler (1985). In statistical machine translation (Koehn, 2009), syntax-based models (Chiang, 2010) [i.e., models that translate from or to syntax trees] have recently seen a lot of progress. It was identified already by Eisner (2003) that the classical linear top-down and bottom-up tree transducers cannot properly handle phenomena (such as rotation) that occur during the translation between natural languages. This result was presented for synchronous context- free grammars [SCFG] (Chiang, 2006), which is a formalism similar in spirit to (and essentially equally expressive as) the syntax-directed transla- tion schemata by Aho and Ullman (1969), which were later refined to the more general bimor- phism approach by Arnold and Dauchet (1982). Instead Eisner (2003) proposes synchronous tree This research was financially supported by the German Research Foundation (DFG) grant MA / 4959 / 1-1. substitution grammars [STSG], which are a re- striction of the synchronous tree adjoining gram- mars [STAG] by Shieber and Schabes (1990). Indeed, STSG have a natural finite-state corre- spondence with the linear and complete bimor- phisms (Arnold and Dauchet, 1982), which did not receive much interest from the theoretical com- puter science community in the sequel. Only with the advent of related models proposed by Galley et al. (2004) and corresponding translation systems following Graehl and Knight (2004), a systematic study of those finite-state tree transformers, now called extended [top-down] tree transducers, was initiated by Maletti et al. (2009). Initial results for extended tree transducers showed that several results for classical tree trans- ducers are no longer valid in the extended set- ting. For example, the composition results for classical tree transducers, derived by Engelfriet (1975) and Baker (1979), no longer hold for ex- tended tree transducers, which was actually al- ready confirmed in the seminal paper by Arnold and Dauchet (1982). However, essentially all rea- sonable extended tree transducers can capture im- portant linguistic transformations (such as rota- tion) without the help of copying. Knight and Graehl (2005) provide a nice overview and estab- lish requirements for an ideal syntax-based trans- lation model. Following this call, extended tree transducers were thoroughly investigated and their basic properties have been established. In this invited talk, we recall the extended tree trans- ducer model and summarize the results reported by Maletti et al. (2009) and Maletti (2011a) en- riched with the recent composition closure results of F  ul  op and Maletti (2013). However, none of the extended tree transducer models that can handle rotation is closed under composition (Maletti et al., 2009). Consequently, May et al. (2010) developed an on-the-fly compo- sition approach that can efficiently evaluate chains of multiple extended tree transducers. With the hope that the composition closure is achieved at a low level, the composition hierarchy of most rel- evant extended tree transducer classes has been in- vestigated in (F  ul  op and Maletti, 2013), where we confirmed that several important composition hi- erarchies are actually infinite. As an alternative to extended tree transducers, we proposed another model originally proposed already by Arnold and Dauchet (1982). This model, nowadays known as multi bottom-up tree transducers [MBOT] fol- lowing the nomenclature of F  ul  op et al. (2004) and F  ul  op et al. (2005), offers closure under com- position (Engelfriet et al., 2009), which removes the need to evaluate chains of models. Maletti (2010) summarizes the advantages following the requirements set by Knight and Graehl (2005), and Maletti (2011b) provides an automatic extrac- tion of an MBOT translation model from the usual training data for syntax-based translation models. This tree-to-tree model was subsequently imple- mented by Braune et al. (2013) in the syntax-based component (Hoang et al., 2009) of the statistical machine translation framework Moses (Koehn et al., 2007). In addition, a string-to-tree MBOT model was developed and evaluated by Seemann et al. (2015a). Finally, several related MBOT mod- els were evaluated by Seemann et al. (2015b) and compared to state-of-the-art models in statistical machine translation. The invited talk will also re- call those efforts and provide the latest develop- ments and evaluations. </chunk></section><section><heading>References </heading><chunk>Alfred V. Aho and Jeffrey D. Ullman. 1969. Syntax directed translations and the pushdown assembler. J. Comput. System Sci., 3(1):3756. Andr  e Arnold and Max Dauchet. 1982. Morphismes et bimorphismes darbres. Theoret. Comput. Sci., 20(1):3393. Brenda S. Baker. 1973. Tree transductions and fam- ilies of tree languages. In Proc. 5th STOC, pages 200206. Association for Computing Machinery. Brenda S. Baker. 1979. Composition of top-down and bottom-up tree transductions. Inform. and Control, 41(2):186213. Fabienne Braune, Nina Seemann, Daniel Quernheim, and Andreas Maletti. 2013. Shallow local multi bottom-up tree transducers in statistical machine translation. In Proc. 51st ACL, pages 811821. As- sociation for Computational Linguistics. David Chiang. 2006. An introduction to synchronous grammars. In Proc. 44th ACL. Association for Com- putational Linguistics. Part of a tutorial given with Kevin Knight. David Chiang. 2010. Learning to translate with source and target syntax. In Proc. 48th ACL, pages 1443 1452. Association for Computational Linguistics. Bruno Courcelle and Paul Franchi-Zannettacci. 1982. Attribute grammars and recursive program schemes. Theoret. Comput. Sci., 17(23):163191 &amp; 235 257. Jason Eisner. 2003. Learning non-isomorphic tree mappings for machine translation. In Proc. 41st ACL, pages 205208. Association for Computa- tional Linguistics. Joost Engelfriet and Heiko Vogler. 1985. Macro tree transducers. J. Comput. System Sci., 31(1):71146. Joost Engelfriet, Eric Lilin, and Andreas Maletti. 2009. Composition and decomposition of extended multi bottom-up tree transducers. Acta Inform., 46(8):561590. Joost Engelfriet. 1975. Bottom-up and top-down tree transformationsa comparison. Math. Systems Theory, 9(3):198231. Joost Engelfriet. 1977. Top-down tree transducers with regular look-ahead. Math. Systems Theory, 10(1):289303. Zolt  an F  ul  op and Andreas Maletti. 2013. Composi- tion closure of -free linear extended top-down tree transducers. In Proc. 17th DLT, volume 7907 of LNCS, pages 239251. Springer. Zolt  an F  ul  op and Heiko Vogler. 1998. Syntax-Directed SemanticsFormal Models Based on Tree Trans- ducers. EATCS Monographs on Theoret. Comput. Sci. Springer. Zolt  an F  ul  op, Armin K  uhnemann, and Heiko Vogler. 2004. A bottom-up characterization of deterministic top-down tree transducers with regular look-ahead. Inf. Process. Lett., 91(2):5767. Zolt  an F  ul  op, Armin K  uhnemann, and Heiko Vogler. 2005. Linear deterministic multi bottom-up tree transducers. Theoret. Comput. Sci., 347(12):276 287. Zolt  an F  ul  op. 1981. On attributed tree transducers. Acta Cybernet., 5(3):261279. Michel Galley, Mark Hopkins, Kevin Knight, and Daniel Marcu. 2004. Whats in a translation rule? In Proc. NAACL, pages 273280. Association for Computational Linguistics. Ferenc G  ecseg and Magnus Steinby. 1984. Tree Au- tomata. Akad  emiai Kiad  o, Budapest. Ferenc G  ecseg and Magnus Steinby. 1997. Tree lan- guages. In Grzegorz Rozenberg and Arto Salomaa, editors, Handbook of Formal Languages, volume 3, chapter 1, pages 168. Springer. Jonathan Graehl and Kevin Knight. 2004. Training tree transducers. In Proc. NAACL, pages 105112. Association for Computational Linguistics. Hieu Hoang, Philipp Koehn, and Adam Lopez. 2009. A unified framework for phrase-based, hierarchical, and syntax-based statistical machine translation. In Proc. 6th IWSLT, pages 152159. National Museum of Emerging Science and Innovation, Tokyo, Japan. Kevin Knight and Jonathan Graehl. 2005. An overview of probabilistic tree transducers for natural language processing. In Proc. 6th CICLing, volume 3406 of LNCS, pages 124. Springer. Philipp Koehn, Hieu Hoang, Alexandra Birch, Chris Callison-Burch, Marcello Federico, Nicola Bertoldi, Brooke Cowan, Wade Shen, Christine Moran, Richard Zens, Chris Dyer, Ondrej Bojar, Alexan- dra Constantin, and Evan Herbst. 2007. Moses: Open source toolkit for statistical machine transla- tion. In Proc. 45th ACL, pages 177180. Associa- tion for Computational Linguistics. Philipp Koehn. 2009. Statistical Machine Translation. Cambridge University Press. Andreas Maletti, Jonathan Graehl, Mark Hopkins, and Kevin Knight. 2009. The power of ex- tended top-down tree transducers. SIAM J. Comput., 39(2):410430. Andreas Maletti. 2010. Why synchronous tree substi- tution grammars? In Proc. NAACL, pages 876884. Association for Computational Linguistics. Andreas Maletti. 2011a. Survey: Weighted extended top-down tree transducers Part II: Application in machine translation. Fundam. Inform., 112(2 3):239261. Andreas Maletti. 2011b. How to train your multi bottom-up tree transducer. In Proc. 49th ACL, pages 825834. Association for Computational Linguis- tics. Jonathan May, Kevin Knight, and Heiko Vogler. 2010. Efficient inference through cascades of weighted tree transducers. In Proc. 48th ACL, pages 1058 1066. Association for Computational Linguistics. William C. Rounds. 1970. Mappings and grammars on trees. Math. Systems Theory, 4(3):257287. Nina Seemann, Fabienne Braune, and Andreas Maletti. 2015a. String-to-tree multi bottom-up tree transduc- ers. In Proc. 53rd ACL, pages 815824. Association for Computational Linguistics. Nina Seemann, Fabienne Braune, and Andreas Maletti. 2015b. A systematic evaluation of MBOT in statis- tical machine translation. In Proc. 15th MT-Summit. Association for Machine Translation in the Ameri- cas. to appear. Stuart M. Shieber and Yves Schabes. 1990. Syn- chronous tree-adjoining grammars. In Proc. 13th CoLing, pages 253258. James W. Thatcher. 1970. Generalized 2 sequential machine maps. J. Comput. System Sci., 4(4):339 367. James W. Thatcher. 1973. Tree automataan informal survey. In Currents in the Theory of Comput., pages 143172. Prentice Hall. </chunk></section></sec_map>