<sec_map><section><chunk>NAACL HLT 2015 Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology: From Linguistic Signal to Clinical Reality Proceedings of the Second Workshop June 5, 2015 Denver, Colorado, USA Sponsor: c 2015 The Association for Computational Linguistics Order print-on-demand copies from: Curran Associates 57 Morehouse Lane Red Hook, New York 12571 USA Tel: +1-845-758-0400 Fax: +1-845-758-2633 curran@proceedings.com Proceedings of the 2nd Workshop on Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology: From Linguistic Signal to Clinical Reality ISBN 978-1-941643-43-3 ii Introduction In the United States, mental health problems are among the most costly challenges we face. The numbers are staggering: An estimated $57.5B was spent on mental health care in 2006. Some 25 million American adults will have an episode of major depression this year, and suicide is the third leading cause of death for people between 10 and 24 years old. The importance of clinical psychology as a problem space cannot be overstated. For clinical psychologists, language plays a central role in diagnosis, and many clinical instruments fundamentally rely on manual coding of patient language. Applying language technology in this domain can have an enormous impact: Many individuals under-report psychiatric symptoms, such as active duty soldiers; or lack the self-awareness to report accurately, such as individuals involved in substance abuse who do not recognize their own addiction. Many people cannot even obtain access to a clinician who is qualified to perform a psychological evaluation, such as those without adequate insurance or who live in rural areas. Bringing language technology to bear on these problems could lead to inexpensive screening measures that may be administered by a wider array of healthcare professionals, suited to the realities of healthcare practice. Researchers have begun targeting such issues, applying computational linguistic methods to clinical psychology with compelling results. Prior to this workshop series, research had looked at identifying emotion in suicide notes, analyzing the language of those with autistic spectrum disorders, aiding the diagnosis of dementia, and screening for depression. ACL 2014 hosted the first Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology Workshop, which brought together the researchers in this nascent field. This workshop was a great success, with accepted papers proposing methods for predicting veteran suicide risk, aiding the diagnosis of dementia, and predicting depression and post-traumatic stress order in social media. NAACL 2015 hosts the second Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology Workshop. Members of the community have come together to organize a hackathon, with a data release and shared task for detecting mental illness as part of this workshop. We hope to build the momentum towards releasing tools and data that can be used by clinical psychologists, and as such, we diverge from the conventional mini-conference workshop format, including practicing clinical psychologists on our program committee and as discussants in the workshop. The ability to communicate relevant computational methods and results clearly, connecting the work to clinical practice, is as important as the quality of the work itself, and more important than research novelty. We received 15 submissions for the main workshop and 3 for the shared task. Of the main workshop submissions, 12 (80%) were accepted: 6 for oral and 6 for poster presentation. Oral presentations will be followed by discussions led by several experts on working with patients and clinical data: Shandra M. Brown Levey, Loring J. Ingraham, John P. Pestian, and Kytja K. S. Voeller. We also have an invited talk from Munmun De Choudhury, an expert in computational social science who has done pioneering work on understanding mental health in social media. We wish to thank everyone who showed interest and submitted a paper, all of the authors for their contributions, the members of the Program Committee for their thoughtful reviews, our clinical discussants for their helpful insights, and all the attendees of the workshop. We also wish to extend thanks to the Association for Computational Linguistics for making this workshop possible, and to Microsoft Research for its generous sponsorship. Meg, Glen, and Kristy iii Organizers: Margaret Mitchell, Microsoft Research (MSR) Glen Coppersmith, Qntfy Kristy Hollingshead, Florida Institute for Human and Machine Cognition (IHMC) Clinical Discussants: Shandra M. Brown Levey, University of Colorado Denver Loring J. Ingraham, George Washington University John P. Pestian, Cincinnati Childrens Hospital Medical Center Kytja K. S. Voeller, Western Institute for Neurodevelopmental Studies and Interventions Program Committee: Steven Bedrick, Oregon Health &amp; Science University Wei Chen, Nationwide Childrens Hospital Glen Coppersmith, Qntfy Mark Dredze, Johns Hopkins University Michael Gamon, Microsoft Research Kimberly Glasgow, Johns Hopkins Applied Physics Laboratory Dan Goldwasser, University of Maryland Graeme Hirst, University of Toronto Christopher Homan, Rochester Institute of Technology Loring J. Ingraham, George Washington University William Jarrold, Nuance Communications Yangfeng Ji, Georgia Institute of Technology Tong Liu, Rochester Institute of Technology Antolin Llorente, Mt. Washington Pediatric Hospital Aimee Mooney, Oregon Health &amp; Science University Eric Morley, Oregon Health &amp; Science University Sylvester Olubolu Orimaye, Monash University Malaysia Cecilia Ovesdotter Alm, Rochester Institute of Technology Craig Pfeifer, The MITRE Corporation Matthew Purver, Queen Mary University of London Philip Resnik, University of Maryland Rebecca Resnik, Mindwell Psychology Bethesda Brian Roark, Google Masoud Rouhizadeh, Oregon Health &amp; Science University Ronald Schouten, Harvard Medical School H. Andrew Schwartz, University of Pennsylvania Richard Sproat, Google Hiroki Tanaka, NAIST Paul Thompson, Dartmouth College Jan van Santen, Oregon Health &amp; Science University Invited Speaker: Munmun De Choudhury, Georgia Tech v vi Table of Contents From ADHD to SAD: Analyzing the Language of Mental Health on Twitter through Self-Reported Di- agnoses Glen Coppersmith, Mark Dredze, Craig Harman and Kristy Hollingshead . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1 Quantifying the Language of Schizophrenia in Social Media Margaret Mitchell, Kristy Hollingshead and Glen Coppersmith . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11 The role of personality, age, and gender in tweeting about mental illness Daniel Preo  tiuc-Pietro, Johannes Eichstaedt, Gregory Park, Maarten Sap, Laura Smith, Victoria Tobolsky, H. Andrew Schwartz and Lyle Ungar . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 21 CLPsych 2015 Shared Task: Depression and PTSD on Twitter Glen Coppersmith, Mark Dredze, Craig Harman, Kristy Hollingshead and Margaret Mitchell . 31 Mental Illness Detection at the World Well-Being Project for the CLPsych 2015 Shared Task Daniel Preo  tiuc-Pietro, Maarten Sap, H. Andrew Schwartz and Lyle Ungar . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 40 Screening Twitter Users for Depression and PTSD with Lexical Decision Lists Ted Pedersen . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 46 The University of Maryland CLPsych 2015 Shared Task System Philip Resnik, William Armstrong, Leonardo Claudino and Thang Nguyen . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 54 Computational cognitive modeling of inflectional verb morphology in Spanish-speakers for the charac- terization and diagnosis of Alzheimers Disease M. Dolores del Castillo, J. Ignacio Serrano and Jesus Oliva . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 61 Recursive Neural Networks for Coding Therapist and Patient Behavior in Motivational Interviewing Michael Tanana, Kevin Hallgren, Zac Imel, David Atkins, Padhraic Smyth and Vivek Srikumar71 Putting Feelings into Words: Cross-Linguistic Markers of the Referential Process Sean Murphy, Bernard Maskit and Wilma Bucci . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 80 Towards Developing an Annotation Scheme for Depressive Disorder Symptoms: A Preliminary Study using Twitter Data Danielle Mowery, Craig Bryan and Mike Conway . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 89 Beyond LDA: Exploring Supervised Topic Modeling for Depression-Related Language in Twitter Philip Resnik, William Armstrong, Leonardo Claudino, Thang Nguyen, Viet-An Nguyen and Jordan Boyd-Graber . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 99 Automated morphological analysis of clinical language samples Kyle Gorman, Steven Bedrick, Geza Kiss, Eric Morley, Rosemary Ingham, Metrah Mohammed, Katina Papadakis and Jan van Santen . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 108 vii Similarity Measures for Quantifying Restrictive and Repetitive Behavior in Conversations of Autistic Children Masoud Rouhizadeh, Richard Sproat and Jan van Santen . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 117 Practical issues in developing semantic frameworks for the analysis of verbal fluency data: A Norwe- gian data case study Mark Rosenstein, Peter Foltz, Anja Vaskinn and Brita Elvevag . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 124 A Computer Program for Tracking the Evolution of a Psychotherapy Treatment Bernard Maskit, Wilma Bucci and Sean Murphy . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 134 viii Workshop Program 2015/06/05 09:0009:15 Opening Remarks Margaret Mitchell, Glen Coppersmith, Kristy Hollingshead 09:1511:00 Oral Presentations, Session 1 From ADHD to SAD: Analyzing the Language of Mental Health on Twitter through Self-Reported Diagnoses Glen Coppersmith, Mark Dredze, Craig Harman and Kristy Hollingshead Quantifying the Language of Schizophrenia in Social Media Margaret Mitchell, Kristy Hollingshead and Glen Coppersmith The role of personality, age, and gender in tweeting about mental illness Daniel Preo  tiuc-Pietro, Johannes Eichstaedt, Gregory Park, Maarten Sap, Laura Smith, Victoria Tobolsky, H. Andrew Schwartz and Lyle Ungar 11:0011:15 Break 11:1511:45 Shared Task CLPsych 2015 Shared Task: Depression and PTSD on Twitter Glen Coppersmith, Mark Dredze, Craig Harman, Kristy Hollingshead and Margaret Mitchell Mental Illness Detection at the World Well-Being Project for the CLPsych 2015 Shared Task Daniel Preo  tiuc-Pietro, Maarten Sap, H. Andrew Schwartz and Lyle Ungar Screening Twitter Users for Depression and PTSD with Lexical Decision Lists Ted Pedersen The University of Maryland CLPsych 2015 Shared Task System Philip Resnik, William Armstrong, Leonardo Claudino and Thang Nguyen 11:3511:45 Discussion Philip Resnik ix 2015/06/05 (continued) 11:4512:45 Poster Presentations Computational cognitive modeling of inflectional verb morphology in Spanish- speakers for the characterization and diagnosis of Alzheimers Disease M. Dolores del Castillo, J. Ignacio Serrano and Jesus Oliva Recursive Neural Networks for Coding Therapist and Patient Behavior in Motiva- tional Interviewing Michael Tanana, Kevin Hallgren, Zac Imel, David Atkins, Padhraic Smyth and Vivek Srikumar Putting Feelings into Words: Cross-Linguistic Markers of the Referential Process Sean Murphy, Bernard Maskit and Wilma Bucci Towards Developing an Annotation Scheme for Depressive Disorder Symptoms: A Preliminary Study using Twitter Data Danielle Mowery, Craig Bryan and Mike Conway Beyond LDA: Exploring Supervised Topic Modeling for Depression-Related Lan- guage in Twitter Philip Resnik, William Armstrong, Leonardo Claudino, Thang Nguyen, Viet-An Nguyen and Jordan Boyd-Graber Automated morphological analysis of clinical language samples Kyle Gorman, Steven Bedrick, Geza Kiss, Eric Morley, Rosemary Ingham, Metrah Mohammed, Katina Papadakis and Jan van Santen 12:4514:00 Lunch 14:0014:45 Invited Talk 14:0014:45 Invited Talk Munmun De Choudhury x 2015/06/05 (continued) 14:4515:00 Break 15:0016:45 Oral Presentations, Session 2 Similarity Measures for Quantifying Restrictive and Repetitive Behavior in Conver- sations of Autistic Children Masoud Rouhizadeh, Richard Sproat and Jan van Santen Practical issues in developing semantic frameworks for the analysis of verbal flu- ency data: A Norwegian data case study Mark Rosenstein, Peter Foltz, Anja Vaskinn and Brita Elvevag A Computer Program for Tracking the Evolution of a Psychotherapy Treatment Bernard Maskit, Wilma Bucci and Sean Murphy 16:4517:00 Closing Remarks xi </chunk></section></sec_map>