<sec_map><section><chunk>ACL-IJCNLP 2015 Proceedings of the ACL 2015 Workshop on Novel Computational Approaches to Keyphrase Extraction July 30, 2015 Beijing, China c 2015 The Association for Computational Linguistics and The Asian Federation of Natural Language Processing Order copies of this and other ACL proceedings from: Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL) 209 N. Eighth Street Stroudsburg, PA 18360 USA Tel: +1-570-476-8006 Fax: +1-570-476-0860 acl@aclweb.org ISBN 978-1-941643-62-4 ii Preface The ACL 2015 Workshop on Novel Computational Approaches to Keyphrase Extraction was held on July 30, 2015 in Beijing, China as part of the 53rd annual meeting of the ACL and the 7th International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing. The workshops goal was to bring together researchers addressing a wide-range of questions pertaining to the keyphrase extraction task as well as domain-specific applications involving the use of keyphrases. The workshop program included two invited talks by researchers who are experts in the fields of data mining, information retrieval, and natural language processing: Prof. Min-Yen Kan from National University of Singapore and Dr. Preslav Nakov, senior scientist at Qatar Computing Research Institute. After a rigorous review process, two long papers and three short papers were selected for inclusion into the workshop proceedings by the Program Committee. We hope that these papers summarize novel findings related to keyphrase extraction and invoke further research interest on this exciting topic. We thank the authors, invited speakers, program committee members, and participants for sharing their research ideas and valuable time to be part of ACL Keyphrase! Organizers: Sujatha Das Gollapalli, Cornelia Caragea, Xiaoli Li, C. Lee Giles iii Organizers: Sujatha Das Gollapalli, Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR, Singapore Cornelia Caragea, University of North Texas, USA Xiaoli Li, Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR, Singapore C. Lee Giles, The Pennsylvania State University, USA </chunk></section><section><heading>Program Committee: </heading><chunk>Marina Danilevsky, IBM Almaden Research Center Fei Liu, Carnegie Mellon University Doina Caragea, Kansas State University Rada Mihalcea, University of Michigan Shibamouli Lahiri, University of Michigan Saurabh Kataria, Palo Alto Research Center Ani Nenkova, University of Pennsylvania Kazi Hasan, IBM Yang Song, Microsoft Research Olena Medelyan, Entopix Min-Yen Kan, National University of Singapore Feifan Liu, Nuance Inc. Niket Tandon, Max-Planck-Institut fur Informatik Preslav Nakov, Qatar Computing Research Institute Fang Yuan, Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR Pucktada Treeratpituk, Ministry Of Science and Technology, Thailand Madian Khabsa, The Pennsylvania State University Invited Speakers: Min-Yen Kan, National University of Singapore Preslav Nakov, Qatar Computing Research Institute v Table of Contents Keywords, Phrases, Clauses and Sentences: Topicality, Indicativeness and Informativeness at Scales Invited talk by Min-Yen Kan . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1 Technical Term Extraction Using Measures of Neology Christopher Norman and Akiko Aizawa . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2 Counting What Counts: Decompounding for Keyphrase Extraction Nicolai Erbs, Pedro Bispo Santos, Torsten Zesch and Iryna Gurevych . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 10 The Web as an Implicit Training Set: Application to Noun Compounds Syntax and Semantics Invited talk by Preslav Nakov . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 18 Reducing Over-generation Errors for Automatic Keyphrase Extraction using Integer Linear Program- ming Florian Boudin . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 19 TwittDict: Extracting Social Oriented Keyphrase Semantics from Twitter Suppawong Tuarob, Wanghuan Chu, Dong Chen and Conrad Tucker . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 25 Identification and Classification of Emotional Key Phrases from Psychological Texts Apurba Paul and Dipankar Das . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 32 vii Workshop Program Thursday, July 30, 2015 9.10-9.30 Opening Remarks 9.30-10.30 Keywords, Phrases, Clauses and Sentences: Topicality, Indicativeness and Infor- mativeness at Scales Invited Talk by Min-Yen Kan 10.30-11.00 Coffee Break 11.00-11.30 Technical Term Extraction Using Measures of Neology Christopher Norman and Akiko Aizawa 11.30-12.00 Counting What Counts: Decompounding for Keyphrase Extraction Nicolai Erbs, Pedro Bispo Santos, Torsten Zesch and Iryna Gurevych 12.00-14.00 Lunch 14.00-15.00 The Web as an Implicit Training Set: Application to Noun Compounds Syntax and Semantics Invited Talk by Preslav Nakov 15.00-15.30 Reducing Over-generation Errors for Automatic Keyphrase Extraction using Integer Linear Programming Florian Boudin 15.30-16.00 Coffee Break 16.00-16.30 TwittDict: Extracting Social Oriented Keyphrase Semantics from Twitter Suppawong Tuarob, Wanghuan Chu, Dong Chen and Conrad Tucker 16.30-17.00 Identification and Classification of Emotional Key Phrases from Psychological Texts Apurba Paul and Dipankar Das 17.00-17.30 Closing Remarks and Discussion ix </chunk></section></sec_map>