<sec_map><section><chunk>ACL-IJCNLP 2015 Proceedings of the First Workshop on Computing News Storylines (CNewsStory 2015) July 31, 2015 Beijing, China c 2015 The Association for Computational Linguistics and The Asian Federation of Natural Language Processing Order copies of this and other ACL proceedings from: Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL) 209 N. Eighth Street Stroudsburg, PA 18360 USA Tel: +1-570-476-8006 Fax: +1-570-476-0860 acl@aclweb.org ISBN 978-1-941643-71-6 ii Introduction This volume contains the proceedings of the 1st Workshop on Computing News Storylines (CNewsStory 2015) held in conjunction with the 53rd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics and the 7th International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (ACL-IJCNLP 2015) at the China National Convention Center in Beijing, on July 31st 2015. Narratives are at the heart of information sharing. Ever since people began to share their experiences, they have connected them to form narratives. The study of storytelling and the field of literary theory called narratology have developed complex frameworks and models related to various aspects of narrative such as plots structures, narrative embeddings, characters perspectives, reader response, point of view, narrative voice, narrative goals, and many others. These notions from narratology have been applied mainly in Artificial Intelligence and to model formal semantic approaches to narratives (e.g. Plot Units developed by Lehnert (1981)). In recent years, computational narratology has qualified as an autonomous field of study and research. Narrative has been the focus of a number of workshops and conferences (AAAI Symposia, Interactive Storytelling Conference (ICIDS), Computational Models of Narrative). Furthermore, reference annotation schemes for narratives have been proposed (NarrativeML by Mani (2013)). The majority of the previous work on narratives and narrative structures have mainly focused on the analysis of fictitious texts. However, modern day news reports still reflect this narrative structure, but they have proven difficult for automatic tools to summarise, structure, or connect to other reports. This difficulty is partly rooted in the fact that most text processing tools focus on extracting relatively simple structures from the local lexical environment, and concentrate on the document as a unit or on even smaller units such as sentences or phrases, rather than cross-document connections. However, current information needs demand a move towards multidimensional and distributed representations which take into account the connections between all relevant elements involved in a story. Additionally, most work on cross-document temporal processing focuses on linear timelines, i.e. representations of chronologically ordered events in time (for instance, the Event Narrative Event Chains by Chambers (2011), or the SemEval 2015 Task 4: Cross Document TimeLines by Minard et al. (2014)). Storylines, though, are more complex, and must take into account temporal, causal and subjective dimensions. How storylines should be represented and annotated, how they can be extracted automatically, and how they can be evaluated are open research questions in the NLP and AI communities. The workshop aimed to bring together researchers from different communities working on representing and extracting narrative structures in news, a text genre which is highly used in NLP but which has received little attention with respect to narrative structure, representation and analysis. Currently, advances in NLP technology have made it feasible to look beyond scenario-driven, atomic extraction of events from single documents and work towards extracting story structures from multiple documents, while these documents are published over time as news streams. Policy makers, NGOs, information specialists (such as journalists and librarians) and others are increasingly in need of tools that support them in finding salient stories in large amounts of information to more effectively implement policies, monitor actions of big players in the society and check facts. Their tasks often revolve around reconstructing cases either with respect to specific entities (e.g. person or organizations) or events (e.g. hurricane Katrina). Storylines represent explanatory schemas that enable us to make better selections of relevant information but also projections to the future. They form a valuable potential for exploiting news data in an innovative way. Albeit small in number, the contributions that are published in this volume do indeed cover the topics we intended to touch upon. We received 12 submissions and accepted 9. Two papers focus on tracking and representing emergent news topics (Tadashi) and develop personalised news aggregation systems (Fedorovsky et al.). Events, the primary source of information and blocks for storylines, are the targets of three papers which tackles different issues such as improving event type detection (Li et al.), the analysis of the properties of sequences of events (Simonson and Davis), and the automatic extraction of iii news agendas as the ability of storylines to direct action (Stalpouskaya and Baden). Notions such as relevance and importance are at the core of two papers: one paper which describes a formal model and a preliminary implementation for automatically extracting storylines from news stream (Vossen et al.), and one paper which proposes a post-retrieval snippet clustering based on pattern structures (Makhalova et al.). Finally, a proposal for storyline representation and evaluation (Laparra et al.) and the adaptation of approaches and methods from the domain of fiction to the news data (Miller et al.) are reported. We would like to thank the members of the Program Committee for their timely reviews. We would also like to thank the authors for their contributions. iv Organizers: Tommaso Caselli, VU University Amsterdam Marieke van Erp, VU University Amsterdam Anne-Lyse Minard, Fondazione Bruno Kessler Mark Finlayson, Florida International University Ben Miller, Georgia State University Jordi Atserias, Yahoo! Barcelona Alexandra Balahur, European Commissions Joint Research Centre Piek Vossen, VU University Amsterdam Program Committee: Sabine Bergler, Concordia University, Canada Matje van de Camp, De Taalmonsters, The Netherlands Erik van der Goot, EC Joint Research Centre, Italy Nathanael Chambers, United States Naval Academy, USA Leon Derczynski, University of Sheffield, UK Anthony Jameson, DFKI, Germany Bernardo Magnini, Fondazione Bruno Kessler, Italy Jarred McGinnis, Logomachy.org, UK Roser Morante, VU University Amsterdam, The Netherlands Silvia Pareti, Google Inc. &amp; University of Edinburgh Ellen Riloff, University of Utah, USA Roser Sauri, Pompeu Fabra University, Spain Hristo Tanev, EC Joint Research Centre, Italy Xavier Tannier, Universite Paris-Sud &amp; LIMSI-CNRS, France Naushad UzZanam, Nuance Communications, Inc. Laure Vieu, IRIT-CNRS - Universite Toulouse III, France Marc Verhagen, Brandeis University, USA v Table of Contents Interactions between Narrative Schemas and Document Categories Dan Simonson and Anthony Davis . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1 Improving Event Detection with Abstract Meaning Representation Xiang Li, Thien Huu Nguyen, Kai Cao and Ralph Grishman . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11 News clustering approach based on discourse text structure Tatyana Makhalova, Dmitry Ilvovsky and Boris Galitsky . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 16 To Do or Not to Do: the Role of Agendas for Action in Analyzing News Coverage of Violent Conflict Katsiaryna Stalpouskaya and Christian Baden . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 21 MediaMeter: A Global Monitor for Online News Coverage Tadashi Nomoto . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 30 Expanding the horizons: adding a new language to the news personalization system Andrey Fedorovsky, Maxim Ionov, Varvara Litvinova, Tatyana Olenina and Darya Trofimova . . 35 Storylines for structuring massive streams of news Piek Vossen, Tommaso Caselli and Yiota Kontzopoulou . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 40 From TimeLines to StoryLines: A preliminary proposal for evaluating narratives Egoitz Laparra, Itziar Aldabe and German Rigau . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 50 Cross-Document Non-Fiction Narrative Alignment Ben Miller, Jennifer Olive, Shakthidhar Gopavaram and Ayush Shrestha . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 56 vii Conference Program 31 July 2015 09:1509:25 Opening Remarks 09:2509:50 Interactions between Narrative Schemas and Document Categories Dan Simonson and Anthony Davis 09:5010:10 Improving Event Detection with Abstract Meaning Representation Xiang Li, Thien Huu Nguyen, Kai Cao and Ralph Grishman 10:1010:30 News clustering approach based on discourse text structure Tatyana Makhalova, Dmitry Ilvovsky and Boris Galitsky 10:3011:00 Coffee Break 11:0011:25 To Do or Not to Do: the Role of Agendas for Action in Analyzing News Coverage of Violent Conflict Katsiaryna Stalpouskaya and Christian Baden 11:2511:45 MediaMeter: A Global Monitor for Online News Coverage Tadashi Nomoto 11:4512:05 Expanding the horizons: adding a new language to the news personalization system Andrey Fedorovsky, Maxim Ionov, Varvara Litvinova, Tatyana Olenina and Darya Trofimova 12:0512:30 Storylines for structuring massive streams of news Piek Vossen, Tommaso Caselli and Yiota Kontzopoulou 12:3014:00 Lunch Break 14:0014.20 From TimeLines to StoryLines: A preliminary proposal for evaluating narratives Egoitz Laparra, Itziar Aldabe and German Rigau 14:2014:40 Cross-Document Non-Fiction Narrative Alignment Ben Miller, Jennifer Olive, Shakthidhar Gopavaram and Ayush Shrestha 14:4015:30 Discussion and Conclusions ix </chunk></section></sec_map>