<sec_map><section><chunk>@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) iii Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) iv Preface: Program Chair We are very pleased to introduce the proceedings of the 20 th Nordic Conference on Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015), held at the Institute of the Lithuanian Language in Vilnius, Lithuania, between May 11 and May 13, 2015. The proceed- ings is published as part of the NEALT Proceedings Series by Linkoping University Electronic Press, and is also publicly available in the ACL Anthology for the first time. NODALIDA have been held bi-annually since 1977, first organized as a friendly gathering in Gothenburg, Sweden to discuss on-going research in computational lin- guistics in the Nordic countries. Nearly 30 years later, in 2006, the Northern European Association for Language Technology (NEALT) was founded to organize NODALIDA and other events in the Nordic countries, the Baltic states, and Northwest Russia to promote research, cooperation and information exchange in the field of language tech- nology in a wide sense. Today, NODALIDA addresses all aspects of computational lin- guistics, natural language processing, and speech technology, including work in closely related neighboring disciplines. The conference has been internationally recognized outside the Nordic regions and submissions are received from all over the world. It is a great honor to serve as the Program Chair for NODALIDA 2015, to be held in Lithuania for the first time. Following the pattern of previous years, the Program Committee invited paper sub- missions in four distinct tracks: regular papers on substantial, original, and unpub- lished research, including empirical evaluation results, where appropriate; student pa- pers on completed or ongoing work, where at least the first author is a student; short papers on smaller, focused contributions, work in progress, negative results, surveys, or opinion pieces; and demonstration papers summarizing a software system or language resource, to be accompanied by a live demonstration at the conference. The conference received 68 submissions from all over Europe as well as from Canada, India, Japan, and the US. We followed the standards of recent NODALIDAs emerged since 2007with high quality technical track with peer-review of all papers, and an acceptance rate of 61%. All submitted papers went through a rigorous review process. The regular, student and short papers were reviewed by three experts in the field while the demonstration papers were reviewed by two experts. The final selec- tion was made by the Program Committee, which was not an easy task due to many submissions with high scores and overall positive reviews, and the time and space con- straints of the two day long main conference. We aimed at achieving balance between regular and short papers, and was more lenient in the student and demo categories. Our goal was to include papers dealing with a wide variety of topics from various regions while maintaining NODALIDAs regional character as the major conference for Nordic research. 42 submissions were accepted for presentation either as long talks, poster presentations, lightning talks with poster presentations, or demos. In the final program, there are 22 regular, 5 student, 8 short, and 7 demonstration papers, all collected in this volume. In addition to the accepted papers, we are proud to present three invited keynote speakers, distinguished researchers from France, Great Britain, and the US, to cover different areas of the conference. Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) v Kevin Knight (University of Southern California) presents work on the use of redundancy information occurring in natural language by humans to improve auto- matic language processing applications, such as summarization or machine transla- tion. Catherine Pelachaud (CNRS-LTCI, TELECOM-ParisTech) talks about how to model virtual agents with socio-emotional capabilities, in particular how we can an- imate laughter and virtual agents who can laugh when interacting with humans. Se- bastian Riedel (University College London) presents his work on teaching machines to read and to reason about what was read. In addition, we followed the quite recent tradition of organizing a local language tutorial on Lithuanian. The conference program also includes four worshops: i) NLP for Computer As- sisted Language Learning, ii) Semantic resources and semantic annotation for Natural Language Processing and the Digital Humanities, iii) Constraint Grammar - Methods, Tools and Applications and iv) Innovative Corpus Query and Visualization Tools. Each workshop has been organized by their own committees, and produced their own pro- ceedings published in the same series. Organizing a conference with a good program is complex and relies on the good- will of many researchers involved in the field. I would like to express my gratitude and appreciation to my fellows on the Program Committee for their hard and invaluable work for sharing the effort of creating the program. A special thanks goes to Stephan Oepen, the program chair of NODALIDA 2013, and NEALTs president, Bolette Sand- ford Pedersen, for generous advice. Wholehearted thanks go to the 62 reviewers for their time and effort to contribute to the reviewing and selection of papers. I am also grateful to the three keynote speakers, the presenter of the local language tutorial, and the workshop organizers! And of course, all the authors who submitted papers de- serve special thanks. Without you, this conference would not take place! In addition, I would also like to acknowledge and thank Nils Blomqvist for professionally serving as the proceedings co-manager. I am also indebted to Lars Ahrenberg, the editor-in-chief of NEALT, for helping the publication of the proceedings in ACL anthology, in paral- lel with Linkoping University Electronic Press, come true. My greatest debt goes to the Institute of the Lithuanian Language, Jolanta Zabarskaite, and in particular Violeta Meili  unait  e for carrying the heavy burden of the local organization, and for being a great host in the picturesque city of Vilnius. Lastly, I am grateful to my colleagues at Department of Linguistics and Philology at Uppsala University for their patience with me during the last year and generously letting me hide from time to time while organizing this conference, and to my nearest and dearestmy twins and friendsfor generously giving me the space to disappear into our world of language technology. I wish you all a fruitful conference and hope you will enjoy NODALIDA 2015! Beata Megyesi (Program Chair) Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) vi Preface: Local Organizer Chair I would like to extend a warm welcome to the participants and guests at NODALIDA 2015. The fact that this conference, with its highly acclaimed status and prominence in the academia, is taking place in Lithuania in 2015 is significant in several ways. We find it very important that such a high-level event, which attracts a great many scientists and graduate students from all over the world, is taking place in a country that has its language classed as one of the less-used. It shows that NEALT understands and supports the involvement of the minor European languages that do not have big tech- nological markets in the processes of supporting multilingualism and multiculturalism both in Europe and on a world-wide scale, which processes are in fact aimed at devel- oping and upgrading language technologies. Needless to say, this kind of involvement is critical to the Lithuanian language. What is more, in the digital age language acquires many new functions, evolving from a tool of communication and a persuader into something that creates added value in the society of knowledge and creative process. Figuratively speaking, the impalpa- bility of the digital world brings forth perfectly tangible things. As John Searle, one of the most prominent contemporary linguistic philosophers, once said words make things. And it is the rapidly developing language technologies that make it happen in the first place. Language technologies facilitate the retrieval of information, manage- ment of different things, communication, and exchange of creative ideas that are rooted in the unique nature of each and every language. Ideas are the backbone of innovation as the key precondition for global development. As a researcher of the Lithuanian lan- guage, I believe that eventually there will be no more minor and major languages in the world, as they all have equal opportunities. And all that thanks to language technolo- gies alone. Another important thing is that NODALIDA 2015 is taking place in a country whose language is considered one of the languages that have preserved the structure of the Indo-European parent language the best, and for a good reason. The structure of the Lithuanian language is indeed very complicated, and its digitalisation poses a signif- icant challenge to scientists. I truly hope that as a result of this conference more re- searchers will discover a passion for tackling difficult problems, such as the Lithuanian language and its next-of-kin, the Latvian language. The future of languages is in the hands of language technologists. Sharing scien- tific expertise, discovering new contacts, meeting old friends, setting up and updating scientific networks, developing and presenting new ideas is what we all expect from NODALIDA 2015. Many thanks to all who have gathered here in Vilnius. Jolanta Zabarskaite (Local Organizer Chair) Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) vii Program Committee Filip Ginter, University of Turku, Finland Kristiina Jokinen, University of Helsinki, Finland Arne Jonsson, Linkoping University, Sweden Violeta Meili  unait  e, Institute of the Lithuanian Language, Lithuania Beata Megyesi (Program Chair), Uppsala University, Sweden Costanza Navarretta, University of Copenhagen, Denmark Stephan Oepen, University of Oslo, Norway Oscar Tackstrom, Google Inc. Organizing Committee Jolanta Zabarskaite Violeta Meili  unait  e Reviewers Yvonne Adesam, University of Gothenburg, Sweden Lars Ahrenberg, Linkoping University, Sweden Krasimir Angelov, University of Gothenburg, Sweden Bernd Bohnet, University of Stuttgart, Germany Janne Bondi Johannessen, University of Oslo, Norway Johan Boye, Royal Technical Institute (KTH), Sweden Diego Ceccarelli, National Research Council, Italy Lin Chen, University of Illinois, USA Koenraad De Smedt, University of Bergen, Norway Rodolfo Delmonte, CaFoscari University Venice, Italy Jens Edlund, Royal Technical Institute (KTH), Sweden Anna Esposito, Second University of Naples, Italy Bjorn Gamback, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Norway Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) viii Gintare Grigonyte, University of Stockholm, Sweden Christian Hardmeier, Uppsala universitet, Sweden Petter Haugereid, NTNU, Trondheim, Norway Katarina Heimann Muhlenbock, University of Gothenburg, Sweden Anna Hjalmarsson, Royal Technical Institute (KTH), Sweden Angelina Ivanova, University of Oslo, Norway Richard Johansson, University of Gothenburg, Sweden Sofie Johansson Kokkinakis, University of Gothenburg, Sweden Jussi Karlgren, Gavagai and KTH, Sweden Mare Koit, University of Tartu, Estonia Marco Kuhlmann, Linkoping University, Sweden Alessandro Lenci, University of Pisa, Italy Krister Linden, University of Helsinki, Finland Christian Lindgren, Lund University, Sweden Diego Marcheggiani, Italian National Research Council, Italy Antonia Marti, University of Barcelona, Spain Mattias Nilsson, Karolinska Institutet, Sweden Joakim Nivre, Uppsala University, Sweden Pierre Nugues, Lund University, Sweden Gustav Oqvist Seimyr, Karolinska Institutet, Sweden Constantin Orasan, University of Wolverhampton, UK Robert Ostling, Stockholm University, Sweden Lilja vrelid, University of Oslo, Norway Patrizia Paggio, University of Copenhagen, Denmark Eva Pettersson, Uppsala University, Sweden Tommi A Pirinen, Dublin City University, Ireland Barbara Plank, University of Copenhagen, Denmark Sampo Pyysalo, University of Turku, Finland Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) ix Siva Reddy, University of Edinburgh, UK Fabio Rinaldi, University of Zurich, Switzerland Eirikur Rognvaldsson, School of Humanities, Iceland Rune Stre, NTNU, Trondheim, Norway Giampiero Salvi, Royal Technical Institute (KTH), Sweden Marina Santini, Nordstedts, Sweden Arne Skjrholt, University of Oslo, Norway Anders Sgaard, University of Copenhagen, Denmark Sara Stymne, Uppsala University, Sweden Torbjrn Svendsen, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Norway Nina Tahmasebi, University of Gothenburg, Sweden Joel Tetreault, Yahoo Labs, USA Jorg Tiedemann, Uppsala University, Sweden Olga Uryupina, University of Trento, Italy Erik Velldal, University of Oslo, Norway Sumithra Velupillai, Stockholm University, Sweden Martin Volk, University of Zurich, Switzerland Jurgen Wedekind, University of Copenhagen, Denmark Mats Wiren, Stockholm University, Sweden Roman Yangarber, University of Helsinki, Finland Heike Zinsmeister, University of Hamburg, Germany Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) x INVITED TALK: How Much Information Does a Human Translator Add to the Original? Kevin Knight ISI, University of Southern California, USA knight@isi.edu </chunk></section><section><heading>Abstract </heading><chunk>It is well-known that natural language has built-in redundancy. By using context, we can often guess the next word or character in a text. Two practical communi- ties have independently exploited this fact. First, automatic speech and translation researchers build language models to distinguish fluent from non-fluent outputs. Second, text compression researchers convert predictions into short encodings, to save disk space and bandwidth. I will explore what these two communities can learn from each others (interestingly different) solutions. Then I will look at the less-studied question of redundancy in bilingual text, addressing questions like "How well can we predict human translator behavior?" and "How much informa- tion does a human translator add to the original?" (This is joint work with Barret Zoph and Marjan Ghazvininejad.) Bio Kevin Knight is Director of Natural Language Technologies at the Information Sciences Institute (ISI) of the University of Southern California (USC), and a Pro- fessor in the USC Computer Science Department. He received a PhD in computer science from Carnegie Mellon University and a bachelors degree from Harvard University. Prof. Knights research interests include machine translation, automata theory, and decipherment of historical manuscripts. Prof. Knight co-wrote the textbook "Artificial Intelligence", served as President of the Association for Com- putational Linguistics, and was a co-founder of the machine translation company Language Weaver, Inc. He is a Fellow of the Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), and the Information Sciences Institute (ISI). Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xi Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xii INVITED TALK: Modeling Socio-Emotional Humanoid Agent Catherine Pelachaud CNRS-LTCI, TELECOM-ParisTech, France catherine.pelachaud@telecom-paristech.fr </chunk></section><section><heading>Abstract </heading><chunk>In this talk, I will present our current work toward endowing virtual agents with socio-emotional capabilities. I will start describing an interactive system of an agent dialoging with human users in an emotionally colored manner. Through its behaviors, the agent can sustain a conversation as well as show various attitudes and levels of engagement. I will present our latest work on laughter. I will address several issues such as: how to animate laughter in a virtual agent looking par- ticularly at rhythmic movements; how to laugh with human participant and how laughing agent is perceived. Bio Catherine Pelachaud is a Director of Research at CNRS in the laboratory LTCI, TELECOM ParisTech. Her research interest includes embodied conversational agent, nonverbal communication (face, gaze, and gesture), expressive behaviors and socio-emotional agents. She is associate editor of several journals among which IEEE Transactions on Affective Computing, ACM Transactions on Inter- active Intelligent Systems and Journal on Multimodal User Interfaces. She has co-edited several books on virtual agents and emotion-oriented systems. Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xiii Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xiv INVITED TALK: Embedding Probabilistic Logic for Machine Reading Sebastian Riedel University College London, UK sebastian.riedel@gmail.com </chunk></section><section><heading>Abstract </heading><chunk>We want to build machines that read, and make inferences based on what was read. A long line of the work in the field has focussed on approaches where language is converted (possibly using machine learning) into a symbolic and relational rep- resentation. A reasoning algorithm (such as a theorem prover) then derives new knowledge from this representation. This allows for rich knowledge to captured, but generally suffers from two problems: acquiring sufficient symbolic background knowledge and coping with noise and uncertainty in data. Probabilistic logics (such as Markov Logic) offer a solution, but are known to often scale poorly. In recent years a third alternative emerged: latent variable models in which entities and relations are embedded in vector spaces (and represented "distribu- tional"). Such approaches scale well and are robust to noise, but they raise their own set of questions: What type of inferences do they support? What is a proof in embeddings? How can explicit background knowledge be injected into embed- dings? In this talk I first present our work on latent variable models for machine reading, using ideas from matrix factorisation as well as both closed and open in- formation extraction. Then I will present recent work we conducted to address the questions of injecting and extracting symbolic knowledge into/from models based on embeddings. In particular, I will show how one can rapidly build accurate rela- tion extractors through combining logic and embeddings. Bio Dr. Riedel is a Senior Lecturer in the Department of Computer Science at Univer- sity College London, leading the Machine Reading lab. He received his MSc and PhD (in 2009) in Computer Science from the University of Edinburgh. He was a researcher at the University of Tokyo, and a postdoc with Andrew McCallum at the University of Massachusetts Amherst. He is an Allen Distinguished Investigator, a Marie Curie CIG fellow, was a finalist for the Microsoft Research Faculty Award in 2013 and recently received a Google Focused Research award. Sebastian is gen- erally interested in the intersection of NLP and machine learning, and particularly interested in teaching machines to read, and to reason with what was read. Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xv Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xvi @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xvii @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xviii @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@ Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xix Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xx CONFERENCE PROGRAM Monday, May 11, 2015 NODALIDA WORKSHOPS 09:00-13:00 Constraint Grammar - Methods, Tools and Applications 09:00-18:00 4th Workshop on NLP for Computer Assisted Language Learning 13:00-18:00 Innovative Corpus Query and Visualization Tools 13:00-17:30 Semantic resources and semantic annotation for Natural Language Processing and the Digital Humanities 19:30 Welcome reception Tuesday, May 12, 2015 MAIN CONFERENCE 09:10 09:30 Opening 09:30 10:30 Keynote Kevin Knight How Much Information Does a Human Translator Add to the Original? 10:30-11:00 Coffee Break 11:00-12:30 Regular papers Parallel session 1 Syntax 11:00-11:30 Eckhard Bick and Tino Didriksen. CG-3 Beyond Classical Constraint Grammar 11:30-12:00 Jostein Lien, Erik Velldal and Lilja vrelid. Improving Cross-Domain Dependency Parsing with Dependency- Derived Clusters 12:00-12:30 Jorg Tiedemann. Improving the Cross-Lingual Projection of Syntactic Dependencies Parallel Session 2 Annotation, Lithuanian NLP 11:00-11:30 Yvonne Adesam, Gerlof Bouma and Richard Johansson. Defining the Eukalyptus forest the Koala treebank of Swedish 11:30-12:00 Loic Boizou, Jolanta Kovalevskaite and Erika Rimkute. Automatic Lemmatisation of Lithuanian MWEs Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xxi 12:00-12:30 Jurgita Kapociute-Dzikiene, Ligita Sarkute and Andrius Utka. The Effect of Author Set Size in Authorship Attribution for Lithuanian Parallel session 3 Speech 11:00-11:30 Robert Reynolds and Francis Tyers. Automatic Word Stress Annotation of Russian Unrestricted Text 11:30-12:00 Dominik Sacha, Yuki Asano, Christian Rohrdantz, Felix Hamborg, Daniel Keim, Bettina Braun and Miriam Butt. Self Organizing Maps for the Visual Analysis of Pitch Contours 12:00-12:30 Julian Zapata and Andreas Seborg Kirkedal. Assessing the Performance of Automatic Speech Recognition Systems When Used by Native and Non-Native Speakers of Three Major Languages in Dictation Workflows 12:30-13:30 Lunch 13:30-14:30 Lightning talks Parallel Session 1 Syntax and Semantics 13:30-13:50 Johan Bos and Malvina Nissim. Uncovering Noun-Noun Compound Relations by Gamification 13:50-14:10 Hector Martinez Alonso, Anders Johannsen, Barbara Plank and Anders Sgaard. Active Learning for Sense Annotation 14:10-14:30 Ildiko Pilan. Helping Swedish words Come to their Senses: Word-Sense Disambiguation Based on Sense Associations from the SALDO Lexicon Parallel Session 2 Sign language and Speech 13:30-13:50 Robert Ostling, Carl Borstell and Lars Wallin. Enriching the Swedish Sign Language Corpus with Part of Speech Tags Using Joint Bayesian Word Alignment and Annotation Transfer 13:50-14:10 Peter Juel Henrichsen. Talebob - an Interactive Speech Trainer for Danish 14:10-14:30 Askars Salimbajevs and Jevgenijs Strigins. Using Sub-Word N-Gram Models for Dealing with OOV in Large Vocabulary Speech Recognition for Latvian Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xxii 14:30-15:00 Coffee break 14:30-16:00 Posters and demos Posters: Johan Bos and Malvina Nissim. Uncovering Noun-Noun Compound Relations by Gamification Peter Juel Henrichsen. Talebob - an Interactive Speech Trainer for Danish Hector Martinez Alonso, Anders Johannsen, Barbara Plank and Anders Sgaard. Active Learning for Sense Annotation Ildiko Pilan. Helping Swedish words Come to their Senses: Word-Sense Disambiguation Based on Sense Associations from the SALDO Lexicon Askars Salimbajevs and Jevgenijs Strigins. Using Sub-Word N-Gram Models for Dealing with OOV in Large Vocabulary Speech Recognition for Latvian Robert Ostling, Carl Borstell and Lars Wallin. Enriching the Swedish Sign Language Corpus with Part of Speech Tags Using Joint Bayesian Word Alignment and Annotation Transfer D e m o s : Magnus Birkenes, Lars Johnsen, Arne Lindstad and Johanne Ostad. From Digital Library to N-Grams: NB N-gram Janne Bondi Johannessen. The Corpus of American Norwegian Speech (CANS) Johan Bos. Open-Domain Semantic Parsing with Boxer Sam Hardwick, Miikka Silfverberg and Krister Linden. Extracting Semantic Frames using hfst-pmatch Arne Neumann. discoursegraphs: A Graph-Based Merging Tool and Converter for Multilayer Annotated Corpora Tommi A Pirinen. OmorfiFree and Open Source Morphological Lexical Database of Finnish Evelina Rennes and Arne Jonsson. A Tool for Automatic Simplification of Swedish Texts Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xxiii 16:00-17:00 Keynote Catherine Pelachaud Modeling socio-emotional humanoid agent 19:00 Conference Dinner Wednesday, May 13, 2015 MAIN CONFERENCE 09:00 -10:00 Keynote Sebastian Riedel Embedding Probabilistic Logic for Machine Reading 10:00 -10:30 Coffee break 10:30-12:00 Regular and student papers Parallel Session 1 Semantics 10:30-11:00 Juhani Luotolahti and Filip Ginter. Sentence Compression For Automatic Subtitling 11:00-11:30 Sigrid Klerke, Hector Martinez Alonso and Anders Sgaard. Looking hard: Eye Tracking for Detecting Grammaticality of Automatically Compressed Sentences 11:30-12:00 Richard Johansson and Luis Nieto Pina. Combining Relational and Distributional Knowledge for Word Sense Disambiguation Parallel Session 2 Syntax and Semantics 10:30-11:00 Malin Ahlberg, Peter Andersson, Markus Forsberg and Nina Tahmasebi. A case study on supervised classification of Swedish pseudo- coordination 11:00-11:30 Eva Pettersson and Joakim Nivre. Improving Verb Phrase Extraction from Historical Text by use of Verb Valency Frames 11:30-12:00 Sampo Pyysalo, Jenna Kanerva, Anna Missila, Veronika Laippala and Filip Ginter. Universal Dependencies for Finnish Parallel Session 3 Student Session 10:30-11:00 Max Berggren, Jussi Karlgren, Robert Ostling and Mikael Parkvall. Inferring the Location of Authors from Words in their Texts Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xxiv 11:00-11:30 Inari Listenmaa and Francis M. Tyers. Automatic Conversion of Colloquial Finnish to Standard Finnish 11:30-12:00 Scharolta Siencnik. Adapting word2vec to Named Entity Recognition 12:00-13:00 Lunch 13:0014:00 Business meeting 14:00-14.30 Coffee break 14:00-15:30 Poster session Long papers: Hector Martinez Alonso, Anders Johannsen, Sussi Olsen, Sanni Nimb, Nicolai Hartvig Srensen, Anna Braasch, Anders Sgaard and Bolette Sandford Pedersen. Supersense tagging for Danish Alexandr Chernov, Volha Petukhova and Dietrich Klakow. Linguistically Motivated Question Classification Jana Gotze and Johan Boye. Resolving Spatial References using Crowdsourced Geographical Data Veronika Laippala, Jenna Kanerva, Anna Missila, Sampo Pyysalo, Tapio Salakoski and Filip Ginter. Towards the Classification of the Finnish Internet Parsebank: Detecting Translations and Informality Mihai Lintean and Vasile Rus. An Optimal Quadratic Approach to Monolingual Paraphrase Alignment Michael Nokel and Natalia Loukachevitch. Topic Models: Accounting Component Structure of Bigrams Short papers: Katarina Heimann Muhlenbock, Sofie Johansson Kokkinakis, Caroline Liberg, Asa af Geijerstam, Jenny Folkeryd, Arne Jonsson, Erik Kanebrant and Johan Falkenjack. A Multivariate Model for Classifying Texts' Readability Gustavo Henrique Paetzold. Using Positional Suffix Trees to Perform Agile Tree Kernel Calculation Steinor Steingrimsson, Sigrun Helgadottir and Eirikur Rognvaldsson. Analysing Inconsistencies and Errors in PoS Tagging in two Icelandic Gold Standards Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xxv Student papers: Vytautas Mickevicius, Tomas Krilavicius Vaidas Morkevicius and Ausra Mackute- Varoneckiene. Automatic Thematic Classification of the Titles of the Seimas Votes Birgitta Ojamaa, Paivi Kristiina Jokinen and Kadri Muischenk. Sentiment Analysis on Conversational Texts 15:30-16:30 Tutorial on Lithuanian Algirdas Saugdargas. Lithuanian Language in the Architecture of Knowledge 16:30-16:40 Closing Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2015) xxvi </chunk></section></sec_map>