<sec_map><section><chunk>ExProM 2015 Second Workshop on Extra-Propositional Aspects of Meaning in Computational Semantics (ExProM 2015) Proceedings June 5, 2015 Denver, Colorado, USA Funding for student travel grants was provided by the National Science Foundation under Grant No. 1523586. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation. c 2015 The Association for Computational Linguistics Order print-on-demand copies from: Curran Associates 57 Morehouse Lane Red Hook, New York 12571 USA Tel: +1-845-758-0400 Fax: +1-845-758-2633 curran@proceedings.com ISBN 978-1-941643-44-0 ii Introduction During the last decade, semantic representation of text has focused on extracting propositional meaning, i.e., capturing who does what to whom, when and where. Several corpora are available, and existing tools extract this kind of knowledge, e.g., semantic role labelers trained on PropBank, NomBank or FrameNet. But propositional semantic representations disregard significant meaning encoded in human language. For example, while sentences (1-2) below share the same propositional meaning regarding verb carry, they do not convey the same overall meaning. In order to truly capture what these sentences mean, extra-propositional aspects of meaning (ExProM) such as uncertainty, negation and attribution must be taken into account. 1. Thomas Eric Duncan likely contracted the disease when he carried a pregnant woman sick with Ebola. </chunk></section><section><chunk>2. Thomas Eric personally told me that he never carried a pregnant woman with Ebola.  The Extra-Propositional Aspects of Meaning (ExProM) in Computational Linguistics Workshop focuses on a broad range of semantic phenomena beyond propositional meaning, i.e., beyond linking propositions and their semantic arguments with relations such as AGENT (who), THEME (what), LOCATION (where) and TIME (when). ExProM is pervasive in human language and, while studied from a theoretical perspective, computational models are scarce. Humans use language to describe events that do not correlate with a real situation in the world. They express desires, intentions and plans, and also discuss events that did not happen or are unlikely to happen. Events are often described hypothetically, and speculation can be used to explain why something is a certain way without a strong commitment. Humans do not always (want to) tell the (whole) truth: they may use deception to hide lies. Devices such as irony and sarcasm are employed to play with words so that what is said is not what is meant. Finally, humans not only describe their personal views or experiences, but also attribute statements to others. These phenomena are not exclusive of opinionated texts. They are ubiquitous in language, including scientific works and news as exemplified below: A better team might have prevented this infection. Some speculate that this was a failure of the internal communications systems. Infected people typically dont become contagious until they develop symptoms. Medical personnel can be infected if they dont use protective gear, such as surgical masks and gloves. You cannot get it from another person until they start showing symptoms of the disease, like fever. You can only catch Ebola from coming into direct contact with the bodily fluids of someone who has the disease and is showing symptoms. iii Weve never seen a human virus change the way it is transmitted. There is no reason to believe that Ebola virus is any different from any of the viruses that infect humans and have not changed the way that they are spread. In its 2015 edition, the Extra-Propositional Aspects of Meaning (ExProM) in Computational Linguistics Workshop was collocated with the Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL) in Denver, CO. The workshop took place on June 5, 2015, and the program consisted of five papers (4 long papers and 1 short paper) and an invited talk by Lauri Karttunen. ExProM 2015 is a a follow-up of two previous events: the 2010 Negation and Speculation in Natural Language Processing Workshop (NeSp-NLP 2010) and ExProM 2012. We would like to thank the authors of papers for their interesting contributions, the members of the program committee for their insightful reviews, and Lauri Karttunen for giving the invited talk. We are grateful to the National Science Foundation for a grant to support student travel to the workshop. iv Organizers: Eduardo Blanco, University of North Texas, USA Roser Morante, VU University Amsterdam, The Netherlands Caroline Sporleder, Universitat Trier, Germany Program Committee: Tim Baldwin - The University of Melbourne Emily M. Bender - University of Washington Cosmin Adrian Bejan - Vanderbilt University Gosse Bouma - University of Groningen Tommaso Caselli - VU University Amsterdam Jacob Eisenstein - Georgia Tech Edward Grefenstette - Google DeepMind Zhou Guadong - Soochow University Ivan Habernal - TU Darmstadt Iris Hendrickx - Radboud University Lori Levin - Carnegie Mellon University Maria Liakata - University of Warwick Erwin Marsi - Norwegian University of Science and Technology Malvina Nissim - University of Groningen Sampo Pyysalo - University of Turku Christopher Potts - Stanford University German Rigau - UPV/EHU Ellen Riloff - University of Utah Paolo Rosso - Universidad Politecnica de Valencia Josef Ruppenhofer - Universitat Hildesheim Roser Sauri - Universitat Pompeu Fabra Erik Velldal - University of Oslo Bonnie Webber - University of Edinburgh Byron C. Wallace, UT Austin Michael Wiegand - Saarland University </chunk></section><section><heading>Invited Speaker: </heading><chunk>Lauri Karttunen, Stanford University v Table of Contents Translating Negation: A Manual Error Analysis Federico Fancellu and Bonnie Webber . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1 Filled Pauses in User-generated Content are Words with Extra-propositional Meaning Ines Rehbein . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 12 A Compositional Interpretation of Biomedical Event Factuality Halil Kilicoglu, Graciela Rosemblat, Michael Cairelli and Thomas Rindflesch . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 22 Committed Belief Tagging on the Factbank and LU Corpora: A Comparative Study Gregory Werner, Vinodkumar Prabhakaran, Mona Diab and Owen Rambow . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 32 Extending NegEx with Kernel Methods for Negation Detection in Clinical Text Chaitanya Shivade, Marie-Catherine de Marneffe, Eric Fosler-Lussier and Albert M. Lai. . . . . .41 vii Workshop Program Friday June 5 2015 8:0009:00 Breakfast 9:159:30 Opening remarks 9:3010:30 Invited Talk: Lauri Karttunen 10:3011:00 Coffee break 11:0012:30 Session 1 11:0011:30 Translating Negation: A Manual Error Analysis Federico Fancellu and Bonnie Webber 11:3012:00 Filled Pauses in User-generated Content are Words with Extra-propositional Mean- ing Ines Rehbein 12:0012:30 A Compositional Interpretation of Biomedical Event Factuality Halil Kilicoglu, Graciela Rosemblat, Michael Cairelli and Thomas Rindflesch 12:302:00 Lunch break ix Friday June 5 2015 (continued) 14:0014:30 Session 2 14:1014:30 Committed Belief Tagging on the Factbank and LU Corpora: A Comparative Study Gregory Werner, Vinodkumar Prabhakaran, Mona Diab and Owen Rambow 14:3015:00 Extending NegEx with Kernel Methods for Negation Detection in Clinical Text Chaitanya Shivade, Marie-Catherine de Marneffe, Eric Fosler-Lussier and Albert M. Lai 15:0015:30 Discussion and closing remarks x </chunk></section></sec_map>