<sec_map><section><chunk>DiscoMT 2015 DISCOURSE IN MACHINE TRANSLATION Proceedings of the Workshop 17 September 2015 Lisbon, Portugal Order print-on-demand copies from: Curran Associates 57 Morehouse Lane Red Hook, New York 12571 USA Tel: +1-845-758-0400 Fax: +1-845-758-2633 curran@proceedings.com c 2015 The Association for Computational Linguistics ISBN: 978-1-941643-32-7 ii Preface It is well-known that texts have properties that go beyond those of their individual sentences and that reveal themselves in the frequency and distribution of words, word senses, referential forms and syntactic structures, including: document-wide properties, such as style, register, reading level and genre; patterns of topical or functional sub-structure; patterns of discourse coherence, as realized through explicit and/or implicit relations be- tween sentences, clauses or referring forms; anaphoric and elliptic expressions, in which speakers exploit the previous discourse con- text to convey subsequent information very succinctly. By the end of the 1990s, these properties had stimulated considerable research in Machine Translation, aimed at endowing machine-translated texts with similar document and discourse properties as their source texts. A period of ten years then elapsed before interest resumed in these topics, now from the perspectives of Statistical and/or Hybrid Machine Translation. This led to the First Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation (DiscoMT) in 2013, held in Sofia, Bulgaria, in connection with the annual ACL conference. Since then, SMT has itself evolved in ways that reflect more interest in and provide more access to needed linguistic knowledge. This evolution is charted in this Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation (DiscoMT 2015), held in Lisbon, Portugal, in connection with EMNLP. Part of this evolution has been the growth of interest in one particular problem: the translation of pronouns whose form in the target language may be constrained in challenging ways by their context. This shared interest has created an environment in which a shared task on pronoun translation or prediction from EnglishtoFrench was able to stimulate responses from groups in China, the Czech Republic, Malta, Sweden, Switzerland, and the UK. In addition to nine papers describing shared task submissions and an overview of the shared task, the submitted systems and the findings (Hardmeier et al., 2015), twelve submissions were accepted for presentation (five as long papers, three as short papers, and four as posters). The papers and posters span the topics of: pronoun translation between languages which differ in pronoun usage (Novak et al., 2015; Guillou and Webber, 2015); explicitation/implicitation in translating discourse connectives (Hoek et al., 2015; Yung et al., 2015); context-aware trans- lation of ambiguous terms (Mascarell et al., 2015; Zhang and Ittycheriah, 2015); assessing document-level properties of MT output, including coherence (Sim Smith et al., 2015; Gong et al., 2015); preserving document-level properties characteristic of register, genre, and other types of text variation (Lapshinova-Koltunski and Vela, 2015; van der Wees et al., 2015; Lapshinova- Koltunski, 2015); and difficulties in preserving them in a purely alignment-based MT framework (Hardmeier, 2015). We hope that workshops such as this one will continue to stimulate work on these aspects of Discourse and Machine Translation, as well as in the many areas not yet represented. iii We would like to thank all the authors who submitted papers to the workshop, as well as all the members of the Program Committee who reviewed the submissions and delivered thoughtful, informative reviews. The Organizers August 15, 2015 References Zhengxian Gong, Min Zhang, and Guodong Zhou. 2015. Document-level machine translation evaluation with gist consistency and text cohesion. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 3340, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computa- tional Linguistics. Liane Guillou and Bonnie Webber. 2015. Analysing ParCor and its translations by state- of-the-art SMT systems. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 2432, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. Christian Hardmeier, Preslav Nakov, Sara Stymne, Jorg Tiedemann, Yannick Versley, and Mauro Cettolo. 2015. Pronoun-focused MT and cross-lingual pronoun prediction: Findings of the 2015 DiscoMT shared task on pronoun translation. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 116, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. Christian Hardmeier. 2015. On statistical machine translation and translation theory. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 168172, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. Jet Hoek, Jacqueline Evers-Vermeul, and Ted J.M. Sanders. 2015. The role of expectedness in the implicitation and explicitation of discourse relations. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 4146, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. Ekaterina Lapshinova-Koltunski and Mihaela Vela. 2015. Measuring registerness in human and machine translation: A text classification approach. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 122131, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. Ekaterina Lapshinova-Koltunski. 2015. Exploration of inter- and intralingual variation of discourse phenomena. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 158167, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. iv Laura Mascarell, Mark Fishel, and Martin Volk. 2015. Detecting document-level context triggers to resolve translation ambiguity. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 4751, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. Michal Novak, Dieke Oele, and Gertjan van Noord. 2015. Comparison of coreference resolvers for deep syntax translation. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 1723, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. Karin Sim Smith, Wilker Aziz, and Lucia Specia. 2015. A proposal for a coherence corpus in machine translation. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 5258, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. Marlies van der Wees, Arianna Bisazza, and Christof Monz. 2015. Translation model adaptation using genre-revealing text features. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Ma- chine Translation, pages 132141, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. Frances Yung, Kevin Duh, and Yuji Matsumoto. 2015. Crosslingual annotation and analysis of implicit discourse connectives for machine translation. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 142152, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. Rong Zhang and Abraham Ittycheriah. 2015. Novel document level features for statistical ma- chine translation. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Discourse in Machine Translation, pages 153157, Lisbon, Portugal. Association for Computational Linguistics. v Organizing Committee Bonnie Webber, University of Edinburgh (chair) Marine Carpuat, University of Maryland (co-chair) Andrei Popescu-Belis, Idiap Research Institute, Martigny (co-chair) Mark Fishel, University of Zurich Christian Hardmeier, Uppsala University Lori Levin, Carnegie Mellon University Preslav Nakov, Qatar Computing Research Institute Ani Nenkova, University of Pennsylvania Lucia Specia, University of Sheffield Jorg Tiedemann, Uppsala University Min Zhang, Soochow University Program Committee Beata Beigman Klebanov, Educational Testing Service Liane Guillou, University of Edinburgh Francisco Guzman, Qatar Computing Research Institute Shafiq Joty, Qatar Computing Research Institute Thomas Meyer, Google, Zurich Michal Novak, Charles University in Prague Lucie Polakova, Charles University in Prague Maja Popovic, DFKI, Berlin Sara Stymne, Uppsala University Yannick Versley, Heidelberg University Marion Weller, University of Stuttgart Shared Task Organizers Christian Hardmeier, Uppsala University Preslav Nakov, Qatar Computing Research Institute Sara Stymne, Uppsala University Jorg Tiedemann, Uppsala University Yannick Versley, Heidelberg University vii Table of Contents Pronoun-Focused MT and Cross-Lingual Pronoun Prediction: Findings of the 2015 DiscoMT Shared Task on Pronoun Translation Christian Hardmeier, Preslav Nakov, Sara Stymne, Jorg Tiedemann, Yannick Versley and Mauro Cettolo . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1 Comparison of Coreference Resolvers for Deep Syntax Translation Michal Novak, Dieke Oele and Gertjan van Noord . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 17 Analysing ParCor and its Translations by State-of-the-art SMT Systems Liane Guillou and Bonnie Webber . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 24 Document-Level Machine Translation Evaluation with Gist Consistency and Text Cohesion Zhengxian Gong, Min Zhang and Guodong Zhou . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 33 The Role of Expectedness in the Implicitation and Explicitation of Discourse Relations Jet Hoek, Jacqueline Evers-Vermeul and Ted J.M. Sanders . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 41 Detecting Document-level Context Triggers to Resolve Translation Ambiguity Laura Mascarell, Mark Fishel and Martin Volk . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 47 A Proposal for a Coherence Corpus in Machine Translation Karin Sim Smith, Wilker Aziz and Lucia Specia . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 52 Part-of-Speech Driven Cross-Lingual Pronoun Prediction with Feed-Forward Neural Networks Jimmy Callin, Christian Hardmeier and Jorg Tiedemann . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 59 Automatic Post-Editing for the DiscoMT Pronoun Translation Task Liane Guillou . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 65 A Document-Level SMT System with Integrated Pronoun Prediction Christian Hardmeier . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 72 Predicting Pronoun Translation Using Syntactic, Morphological and Contextual Features from Parallel Data Sharid Loaiciga . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 78 Rule-Based Pronominal Anaphora Treatment for Machine Translation Sharid Loaiciga and Eric Wehrli . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 86 Pronoun Translation and Prediction with or without Coreference Links Ngoc Quang Luong, Lesly Miculicich Werlen and Andrei Popescu-Belis . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 94 Predicting Pronouns across Languages with Continuous Word Spaces Ngoc-Quan Pham and Lonneke van der Plas . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 101 Baseline Models for Pronoun Prediction and Pronoun-Aware Translation Jorg Tiedemann . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 108 A Maximum Entropy Classifier for Cross-Lingual Pronoun Prediction Dominikus Wetzel, Adam Lopez and Bonnie Webber . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 115 Measuring Registerness in Human and Machine Translation: A Text Classification Approach Ekaterina Lapshinova-Koltunski and Mihaela Vela . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 122 ix Translation Model Adaptation Using Genre-Revealing Text Features Marlies van der Wees, Arianna Bisazza and Christof Monz . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 132 Crosslingual Annotation and Analysis of Implicit Discourse Connectives for Machine Translation Frances Yung, Kevin Duh and Yuji Matsumoto . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 142 Novel Document Level Features for Statistical Machine Translation Rong Zhang and Abraham Ittycheriah . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 153 Exploration of Inter- and Intralingual Variation of Discourse Phenomena Ekaterina Lapshinova-Koltunski . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 158 On Statistical Machine Translation and Translation Theory Christian Hardmeier . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 168 x Workshop Program Thursday, September 17, 2015 09:0010:30 Session 1 09:0009:05 Introduction 09:0509:35 Pronoun-Focused MT and Cross-Lingual Pronoun Prediction: Findings of the 2015 DiscoMT Shared Task on Pronoun Translation Christian Hardmeier, Preslav Nakov, Sara Stymne, Jorg Tiedemann, Yannick Versley and Mauro Cettolo 09:3509:50 Comparison of Coreference Resolvers for Deep Syntax Translation Michal Novak, Dieke Oele and Gertjan van Noord 09:5010:15 Analysing ParCor and its Translations by State-of-the-art SMT Systems Liane Guillou and Bonnie Webber 10:1510:30 Poster Boaster 10:3011:00 Coffee Break 11:0012:30 Session 2a: Regular Track Posters Document-Level Machine Translation Evaluation with Gist Consistency and Text Cohesion Zhengxian Gong, Min Zhang and Guodong Zhou The Role of Expectedness in the Implicitation and Explicitation of Discourse Relations Jet Hoek, Jacqueline Evers-Vermeul and Ted J.M. Sanders Detecting Document-level Context Triggers to Resolve Translation Ambiguity Laura Mascarell, Mark Fishel and Martin Volk A Proposal for a Coherence Corpus in Machine Translation Karin Sim Smith, Wilker Aziz and Lucia Specia xi Thursday, September 17, 2015 (continued) 11:0012:30 Session 2b: Posters Related to Oral Presentations On Statistical Machine Translation and Translation Theory Christian Hardmeier Exploration of Inter- and Intralingual Variation of Discourse Phenomena Ekaterina Lapshinova-Koltunski Measuring Registerness in Human and Machine Translation: A Text Classification Approach Ekaterina Lapshinova-Koltunski and Mihaela Vela Translation Model Adaptation Using Genre-Revealing Text Features Marlies van der Wees, Arianna Bisazza, Christof Monz Crosslingual Annotation and Analysis of Implicit Discourse Connectives for Machine Translation Frances Yung, Kevin Duh, Yuji Matsumoto 11:0012:30 Session 2c: Shared Task Posters Part-of-Speech Driven Cross-Lingual Pronoun Prediction with Feed-Forward Neural Networks Jimmy Callin, Christian Hardmeier and Jorg Tiedemann Automatic Post-Editing for the DiscoMT Pronoun Translation Task Liane Guillou </chunk></section><section><heading>A Document-Level SMT System with Integrated Pronoun Prediction Christian Hardmeier </heading><chunk>Predicting Pronoun Translation Using Syntactic, Morphological and Contextual Features from Parallel Data Sharid Loaiciga Rule-Based Pronominal Anaphora Treatment for Machine Translation Sharid Loaiciga and Eric Wehrli Pronoun Translation and Prediction with or without Coreference Links Ngoc Quang Luong, Lesly Miculicich Werlen and Andrei Popescu-Belis xii Thursday, September 17, 2015 (continued) Predicting Pronouns across Languages with Continuous Word Spaces Ngoc-Quan Pham and Lonneke van der Plas Baseline Models for Pronoun Prediction and Pronoun-Aware Translation Jorg Tiedemann A Maximum Entropy Classifier for Cross-Lingual Pronoun Prediction Dominikus Wetzel, Adam Lopez and Bonnie Webber 12:3014:00 Lunch Break 14:0015:30 Session 3 14:0014:25 Measuring Registerness in Human and Machine Translation: A Text Classification Approach Ekaterina Lapshinova-Koltunski and Mihaela Vela 14:2514:50 Translation Model Adaptation Using Genre-Revealing Text Features Marlies van der Wees, Arianna Bisazza and Christof Monz 14:5015:15 Crosslingual Annotation and Analysis of Implicit Discourse Connectives for Machine Translation Frances Yung, Kevin Duh and Yuji Matsumoto 15:1515:30 Novel Document Level Features for Statistical Machine Translation Rong Zhang and Abraham Ittycheriah 15:3016:00 Coffee Break 16:0017:30 Session 4 16:0016:25 Exploration of Inter- and Intralingual Variation of Discourse Phenomena Ekaterina Lapshinova-Koltunski 16:2516:40 On Statistical Machine Translation and Translation Theory Christian Hardmeier 16:4017:30 Final Discussions and Conclusions xiii </chunk></section></sec_map>