<sec_map><section><chunk>Supplemental Material for the Paper: Optimizing an Approximation of ROUGE a Problem-Reduction Approach to Extractive Multi-Document Summarization Maxime Peyrard and Judith Eckle-Kohler Research Training Group AIPHES and UKP Lab Computer Science Department, Technische Universit  at Darmstadt www.aiphes.tu-darmstadt.de, www.ukp.tu-darmstadt.de </chunk></section><section><heading>1 Submodularity of </heading><chunk>Let S = {s i |i m} be a set of sentences and (S) its ROUGE-N approximation: (S) = n i=1 (s i ) a,bS,a =b (a b) (1) To prove the submodularity of , we prove that follows the diminishing returns property: S T and a sentence a: (S a) (S) (T a) (T ) Proof: Let S = {s i |i m} and T = {t i |i l} be two sets of sentences such that S T . We study the following difference: (S a) (S) (  (T a) (T )) (2) We recall the formula for any set X and any sen- tence a: (X a) = (X) + (a) (X a) (3) When applied to equation (2) we obtain: (T a) (S a) (4) We recall the definition of (X) for any set X: (X) = 1 R N gX 1[freq(g) ] (5) S T implies S a T a. Therefore we can split (T a) and the expression (4) becomes: 1 R N gSa 1[freq(g) ] + 1 R N gT a\Sa 1[freq(g) ] 1 R N gSa 1[freq(g) ] (6) Which can be simplified to: 1 R N gT a\Sb 1[tfidf(g) ] (7) This is a sum of positive terms and it is therefore positive. This proves that expression (2) is 0 which is equivalent to: (S a) (S) (T a) (T ) (8) Which concludes the proof of the submodularity of . 2 System Output Samples Topic d081a (DUC-2002): More than 4,000 workers at a coal mine in the southern city of Jastrzebie went on strike today to demand legalization of Solidarity and higher wages, a spokeswoman said. Andrzej Andrzejczak, head of the Morcinek mine strike committee, said: We support all of the demands of the July Manifesto mine workers. Romanians appear solidly op- posed to the strike, angered by the miners de- mands for an average wage of the equivalent of Dollars 290 a month. Strikes were also reported in the Pechora Coal Basin in the Russian repub- lic, and Chervonograd in the western Ukraine, of- ficial media said. By evening, 14 mines in the region, home of the countrys third-largest coal fields, were reported at a standstill. Some of the miners at the Karl Marx,Chernovonyy Zhovten, Chervonyy Profinter, and Yunkom pits joined the strike. The strike in Jastrzebie, about 275 miles southwest of Warsaw, comes on the eighth anniversary of the founding of the outlawed trade federation. Most of the countrys 1.2 million coal miners are still working, but output in some key regions has been halved, saddling Gorbachev with a substantial labor and fuel problem even as he struggles to revive the Soviet economy. Topic d30010t (DUC-2003): The Islamic mili- tant group Hamas, which has been trying to sab- otage the peace accord, claimed responsibility for the 9:45 a.m. (0745 GMT) attack in the Mahane Yehuda market, police said. The blast killed two assailants, wounded 21 Israelis and prompted Is- rael to suspend implementation of the peace ac- cord with the Palestinians. Palestinian officials condemned the attack, but accused Prime Min- ister Benjamin Netanyahu of political blackmail for holding up the agreement that was to give the Palestinians another 13 percent of the West Bank. In response, Israels Cabinet suspended im- plementation of the new peace accord with the Palestinians. Topic d30042t (DUC-2003): LONDON (AP) Libyan leader Moammar Gadhafi said the suspects in the Lockerbie bombing are very happy to be tried in the Netherlands, and he hoped the trial would lead to a better relationship with the United States. African countries voted in June to ignore the U.N. flight ban that was imposed in 1992 to try and force Libya to hand over for trial two sus- pects wanted in the 1988 bombing of an American airliner over Lockerbie, Scotland. Libya has been under U.N. sanctions since 1992 to force it to hand over the two defendants in the Lockerbie case. </chunk></section></sec_map>